<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuation, or second part, of the most pleasant and delightful history of Reynard the fox containing much matter of pleasure and content : written for the delight of young men, pleasure of the aged and profit of all : to which is added many excellent morals.</title>
            <title>Reynard the Fox. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12633077</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12633077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 348:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuation, or second part, of the most pleasant and delightful history of Reynard the fox containing much matter of pleasure and content : written for the delight of young men, pleasure of the aged and profit of all : to which is added many excellent morals.</title>
                  <title>Reynard the Fox. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[111] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Edward Brewster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In prose.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [111].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ lines">
                     <desc>〈1… lines〉</desc>
                  </gap>SECOND PART,</hi> OF THE Moſt Pleaſant and Delightful HISTORY OF Reynard the Fox. Containing Much Matter of Pleaſure and Content. <hi>WRITTEN</hi> For the Delight of Young Men, Pleaſure of the Aged, and Profit of all.</p>
            <p>To which is added many Excellent Morals.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here read the</hi> Fox, <hi>his Nature, and his Art,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who in this Story acts the greateſt Part.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him here you find advanced highly, and</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In this his Grandeur for a time to ſtand;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till he aſpiring further, Treachery</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Contrived, and did for his</hi> Treaſon <hi>die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewſter,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Crane</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church yard,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is well known that publick Works neceſſarily undergo a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cenſure; and how diligently careful ſoever any Man is, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth this or that to the view of all, he ſhall meet with praiſe or diſpaiſe, more frequently according to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or affection of the Cenſurer, than according to the worth or inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of what he preſents. Therefore ſince I beg not the Patronage of any, nor would I by any Man be miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and ſo cauſleſly cenſured,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:3"/> as an impertinent Writer: I have to the ſubſequent <hi>Work</hi> (which I was minded to have committed to the Preſs without Marginal Notes) added a <hi>Moral,</hi> or <hi>Expoſition</hi> of my own; in doing which, I hope no Man will be ſo diſingenious as to wreſt my words to a ſenſe contrary to my true and proper intent.</p>
            <p>I, in the following Hiſtory, aim not at the reproach or ſlander of any Man or Men whatſoever; but do only deſire thy Content and Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with delight and profit. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Read and peruſe this Little Book, when care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And penſive thoughts to be expelled are.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HOw the King and <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox conſulted together about chuſing a chief Prelate, in the place of <hi>Bellin</hi> the Ram, and how <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf was choſen, &amp;c. Chap. 1.</item>
               <item>How the Fox adviſed the Wolf and his Children to wear <hi>Bellin</hi>'s Gown, and the Clothing of <hi>Bellin</hi>'s Kindred. Chap. 2.</item>
               <item>How the Fox communed with the King about <hi>Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim's</hi> Doubt, and thereupon Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was ſent for to Court, &amp;c. Chap. 3.</item>
               <item>How the Bear and Cat conſpired Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi>'s Death &amp;c. Chap. 4.</item>
               <item>Of the Aſſembly of the Commons, &amp;c. Ch. 5.</item>
               <item>How the King feaſted his Nobles. Chap. 6.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:4"/>
               <item>Of the Diſcourſe between the King and <hi>Reynard</hi> about the advancement of the Bear and Cat, &amp;c. Chap. 7.</item>
               <item>How the Fox, Bear and Cat, were honoured, &amp;c. Chap. 8.</item>
               <item>How the Wolf went to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> to diſcourſe with his Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> &amp;c. Chap. 9.</item>
               <item>How the Fox behaved himſelf in his Office, and of two Cauſes decided by him. Chap. 10.</item>
               <item>How the Fox liberally beſtowed what he got, &amp;c. Chap. 11.</item>
               <item>How <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, informed <hi>Reynard</hi> of what paſſed at a Meeting of the Lords. Ch. 12.</item>
               <item>Of the Diſcourſe between the Fox and Wolf, and of another Meeting of the Lords. Chap. 13.</item>
               <item>Of their laſt Meeting, and how they determined to ſurpriſe the King, and Court, &amp;c. Chap. 14.</item>
               <item>How Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libard, and his Couſin <hi>Slylook</hi> revealed their Treaſon to the King. Ch. 15.</item>
               <item>How the Forces of the Lords met at the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, &amp;c. and how the Traytors were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed. Chap. 16.</item>
               <item>How the Fox conſulting with <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his own Caſtle, &amp;c. Chap. 17.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:4"/>
               <item>How the Fox was purſued, &amp;c. Chap. 18.</item>
               <item>The Examination of Traytors and Priſoners taken, &amp;c. Chap. 19.</item>
               <item>How the Fox and his Soldiers made Incurſions, &amp;c. Chap. 20.</item>
               <item>The King Summons the Fox to ſurrender his Caſtle, &amp;c. Chap. 21.</item>
               <item>The Fox aſſaults the Kings Camp in the Night, &amp;c. Chap. 22.</item>
               <item>The King proclaims all Traytors that aſſiſt <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> &amp;c. Chap. 23.</item>
               <item>How the Fox's Caſtle was ſtormed, and all but himſelf killed, and he taken alive. Ch. 24.</item>
               <item>Of the Diſſolution of the Kings Army, and how the Fox was carryed Priſoner to the Court. Ch. 25.</item>
               <item>The Fox examined. Chap. 26.</item>
               <item>His Confeſſion and Execution, as alſo of all the other Traytors, &amp;c. Chap. 27.</item>
               <item>How the King and the Nobles ruminated the Fox's Confeſſion. Chap. 28.</item>
               <item>How the King made Proclamation, no Beaſt ſhould walk diſguiſed, &amp;c. Chap. 29.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>How the King cauſed three of the Ram's Kindred to be brought before him, &amp;c. Chap. 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How the Wolves were ſuddenly ruined. Chap. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How the King diſtributed the Wealth of the Wolves among the Commons, and then openly ſhewed his love to <hi>Bellin's</hi> Kindred, &amp;c. Chap. 32.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:5"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART Of the Pleaſant and Delightful HISTORY OF Reynard the FOX.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King and <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox conſulted together about chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a chief Prelate in the place of <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>in</hi> the Ram, who (as you heard in the former Part) was convicted of the murder of <hi>Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Hare (though falſly), and ſo put to Death, and how <hi>Iſeg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>im</hi> the Wolf was made chief Prelate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Fox and be reconciled.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOW</hi> after the Fox his Vidory againſt <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, he was not only honoured by the King and all his Subjects with the Title of Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e grew very inward and familiar with the King himſelf, inſomuch as none could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e admitted to any
<pb facs="tcp:64820:6"/> private conference with his Majeſty, unleſs he firſt made way by the favour of the Lord <hi>Reynard.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Moſt puiſſant King, the cauſe of my ſilence was not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was unwilling to undergo any charge or trouble for the good of your Majeſty and whole Kingdom, but becauſe I was aſhamed of the diſcord that had been between my Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> my ſelf, and ſome other of your Loyal Subjects, about matters not worthy to be mentioned in ſo noble an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory; for that cauſe only was I ſilent. We, ſaid the King, remit and forgive all that hath paſſed between my Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> your ſelf, or any other, and will have no more mention made thereof. My Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> hath highly commended you to me, which ſurely no enemy would do. He hath alſo praiſed Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> ſo, as I will not forget to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him alſo. And for Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> becauſe he is ſwift of foot, and fit for imployment, alſo politick and ſubtil, I (as ſoon as opportunity ſerves) will think of ſome office, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he may benefit himſelf, and pleaſe me.</p>
               <p>With theſe words they were all highly contented; the Wolf gave his hand to the Fox in token of friendſhip; the Bear and Cat alſo ſhook hands with the Fox. After theſe Ceremonies were paſſed, they all ſate down. And by a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Vote, Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was choſe chief Prelate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox adviſed the Wolf and his Children to wear <hi>Bellin</hi>'s Gown, and the cloathing of <hi>Bellin</hi>'s kindred.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Fox and Wolf being thus reconciled, held a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel together how they might ſtrengthen each other in the power they had thus obtained. The Fox begun his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in this manner: My moſt dear Uncle, I remembring the wrong I did you more than once, and now by the Kings favour, having an opportunity to recompence you, and my Couſin <hi>Bruin,</hi> but you eſpecially, I think I have done it to purpoſe. You have indeed, good Couſin, replied the Wolf, and I and mine ſhall always acknowledg our ſelves behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to you, not only for the time preſent, but ever after du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life. But how I ſhall paſs the cenſure of the commons I cannot tell. Tuſh, ſaid the Fox, let me alone for that, do but follow my advice and all ſhall be well: your advice Couſin, ſaid the <hi>Wolf,</hi> that I will as long as I have breath. Well then, quoth the Fox, do thus; firſt of all, trim your ſelf handſomly, then take <hi>Bellin</hi>'s furr Gown, and make it as fit to your body, as is poſſible, that head ears, and all may be covered; having done this, thoſe Beaſts which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hated and fled from you will now follow, love, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore you, eſpecially if you under that garment conceal your <note place="margin">Covetous Perſons are eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to diſguiſe themſelves, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble their churliſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fit.</note> own churliſh nature; pardon me Uncle, that I ſpeak ſo. Good Couſin, ſaid Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> think not that I will take offence, where I am to take advice. Well then, if it be ſo ſaid the Fox, I will proceed further; I beſeach you good Uncle, as you love your ſelf and me, ſhew not your teeth at any time, when you are among the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the day time, in the night uſe your liberty, Proviſion muſt be had You ſpeak wiſely ſaith the Wolf, I could never have thought of all this; but good Couſin tell me what I ſhall do, when I come to ſay maſſe, the hoarſneſs of my voice will bewray me. O good Uncle, ſaid the Fox, are you ſo weak, as not
<pb facs="tcp:64820:11"/>
                  <figure/> to find an excuſe for that? tell them, to whom you are to read; that you have gotten a grievous cold. I but Couſin, ſaid the Wolf, that excuſe will ſerve but once. Ah Uncle,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:11"/> ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> if you mean to thrive in your office, you muſt not ſtick to lye apace. Beſides you being chief, need not appear above once a year, your children, and the youngeſt of your kindred have not ſo ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe a voice as you; when they grow old, they muſt read but ſeldom, but now being young they will ſtand you in good ſtead, if they be exactly cloathed with the Gowns of <hi>Bellin</hi>'s kindred; otherwiſe Uncle all is nothing worth: and be ſure to give them the ſame advice I now give you, that is, not to ſhew their teeth in the ray time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Indeed Uncle, I wonder you ſhould think the excuſe of ſaying you have a cold, will not hold water; do you not well know, that the <hi>Ram</hi>'s Kindred have colds often, and cough much. It is true good Couſin, ſaid the <hi>Wolf,</hi> I well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, for when I went to hunt for any of them in the night, I uſually was directed to the place where they were by their coughing. Well then ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> I hope Uncle you own my Counſel as right and good. Yes with all my heart Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, ſaid <hi>Iſegrim:</hi> but now I think of it, you ſpake of my Children and Kindred; I perceive not as yet that any thing was ſaid of them by the King and Lords at this laſt counſel. Uncle, ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> you ſeem to be very ſerupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and to doubt where there is no cauſe; know you not that every Captain puts who he will in place under him, and why not every chief Prelate? Blame me not good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, ſaid <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> for I fear the Commons, ſo ſoon as they hear my name, will all cry out, Not <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> not <hi>Iſegrim. Well</hi> Uncle, ſaid the Fox, if that be your ſuſpition we will ſeek ſome way to avoid what you moſt fear. I my ſelf will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to the King, and acquaint him what hath paſſed between us, as alſo with this moſt material cauſe of fear: and when I have communed with him for ſome time, I will requeſt him to ſend for you, then do you be ſure to come (with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>'s Gown exactly fitted to your Body) into the Kings Preſence, and doubt not but the ſucceſs ſhall anſwer your deſire. In the mean while, let us both go home to our R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſts, and early in the Morning I purpoſe to go to the King; do you wait in readineſs at home, till you are ſent for. So
<pb facs="tcp:64820:12"/> the Fox returned to his Caſtle, and the Wolf to his own houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox communed with the King, touching Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi>'s doubt, and thereupon Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was ſent for to Court, and created Earl of <hi>Pitwood.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>EArly in the morning the Fox came to Court, and being ſuddenly admitted, after obeyſance made, he ſaid, Hail my Soveraign Lord. The King ſeeing him, looked plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly upon him, and ſaid, what are you and your Uncle good Friends? Yes, ſaid the Fox, I humbly thank your Majeſty, all malice and rancor is laid aſide; and all the evening laſt. I was inſtructing him how he ſhould behave himſelf in this high Office your M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jeſty hath conferred upon him. You did well <hi>Reynard,</hi> ſaid the King; but did you mind him of wearing <hi>Bellin</hi>'s fur Gown? Yes noble Sir, ſaid the Fox and he is ſo far reſolved of it, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at I judg ere this he hath fitted the Gown to his own body. If ſo, ſaith the King, it is well; then there is no doubt but he will be well liked of. I have given commandment already, that the heads of all the families of the Commons be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appear here, after the third day, now next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Therefore I would h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> at the time appointed Then the Fox ſaid, ready he will be to be ſure; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f he obſerve all that I adviſed him to, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly gain the Commons to be on his ſide. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there is one thing which troubles him, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s me ſuſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us alſo, and that is, leſt when your Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall preſent him by the name of Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> which name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Commons know, they immediately (not mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Perſon) cry out, No <hi>Iſegrim</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Iſegrim</hi> 'Tis true <hi>Reynard,</hi> ſaid the King, this is a conſiderable matter, and I wiſh I could remedy the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me. Sir, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id the Fox, you may very well; for if your Majeſty be pleaſed to honour
<pb facs="tcp:64820:12"/> him with the title of Count, it matters not of how mean a place, he ſhall bear the name of that place, and not his own name any longer. Well then ſaid the King, I will do ſo; here is a Wood, not far from this place near his own houſe, and it is called <hi>Pitwood,</hi> that Wood I will ſettle upon him and his heirs for ever, and he ſhall be created E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl of <hi>Pitwood.</hi> Therefore ſend for him immediately to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us. Then <hi>Reynard</hi> ſtepping forth called to Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> who waited in the Court, and commanded him to go pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and bring Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> to the Kings preſence; Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> ran ſpeedily to the Houſe, and when he had entred the Houſe and ſaw Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> he knew him not, until he had more ſtrictly obſerved his countenance and diſage, then he knew him, and ſaid; Certes, I knew you not Sir in this new faſhioned Gown; the King hath ſent to ſpeak with you preſently So away went the Wolf and <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat to the Court. When they came there, <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox came forth, and conducted his Uncle into the Kings preſence, and ſaid; here moſt noble Prince is your lately made chief Prelate, is he not very trim and neat? Yes, Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> ſaid the King, I like him paſſing well; but had you not told me how he was dreſſed. I ſhould ſcarcely have known him; ſure his beard is ſhaved, or elſe he ſeems younger than when we ſaw him laſt. Mighty Sir, ſaid the Fox, I adviſed him to trim himſelf thus, judging it moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; beſides I have given him other particular Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which I hope he will obſerve. Then the King tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> ſaid, aſſuredly Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> you have found our Couſin <hi>Reynard</hi> to be your moſt faithful friend, not only by adviſing you what to do, but alſo by informing us, how to aſſure and confirm that honour on you, which we and our Lords have beſtowed ſo freely on your ſelf and on no other; and that is, by conferring a further title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; that ſo your name (ſo dreadful to the Commons), may be laid aſide, and your other Title (being unknown to them), find acceptance and applauſe with them all. The Wolf hearing this, bowed ſo low, as his mouth touched the
<pb facs="tcp:64820:13"/> ground, then raiſing himſelf a little, he began to ſpeak in this manner:</p>
               <p>Moſt puiſſant King, how infinitely am I obliged to your Majeſty, and to the noble Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> here preſent; and that in a time, when I leaſt of all expected any favour from your ſelf, and leſs from him (whom I hated, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I here before your Majeſty beg his pardon), of whoſe loyalty your Majeſty hath undoubtedly had ſufficient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, otherwiſe your Princely wiſdom could not have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced one, rendred ſo vile by me, and other of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for which I here again humbly beg your Majeſties pardon. Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> you are already pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaid the King, therefore riſe up (for Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> had proſtrated himſelf on the ground), and hearken to what I ſhall further ſay. I have not only pardoned you already, but I do now alſo, beſides the honour of chief Prelate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer on you the Earldom of <hi>Pitwood,</hi> which Wood you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly know, for it lies near your Manſton Houſe; that <hi>Wood</hi> I give to you, your heirs, and ſucceſſors for ever; and after the name of that <hi>Wood,</hi> ſo ſhall you be called e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after, and your old name <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> ſhall be no more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, but your title ſhall run thus: Count of <hi>Pitwood,</hi> Lord Paramount; and for brevity ſake, you ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Lord <hi>Pitwood. When</hi> the King had ended his ſpeech, <hi>Iſegrim</hi> (almoſt ready to leap out of his skin for joy) knew not what to ſay; but bowing himſelf with great reverence to the King and the Fox, he in all humility acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Kings immenſe bounty toward him, and the Foxes great love he would never forget; beſides he added, that in the exerciſe of his Function, he would ſtudy nothing ſo much as the Kings intereſt; and that of his own profit he would be always leaſt mindful, with many other ſuch like proteſtations; yet in all theſe he lyed egregiouſly, as you ſhall hear anon:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Bear and the Cat offended at the great Honours of Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> conſpired his death; and how the Fox pacified them till the great Aſſembly of the Commons was over.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHen</hi> the rumour of the Wolf's great Preferments was ſpread among the Nobles, Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear, and Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat hearing thereof, ſtomacked the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not a little. And therefore reaſoned among themſelves thus; How much is this Caitiff the greateſt murtherer of all Beaſts, advanced to Honour above us! if we ſuffer him to abide in this height, we muſt neceſſarily be his Vaſſals: beſides, how great ſoever our grievances be, we can never find redreſs becauſe the Fox his great friend is the Kings only Favourite; ſo that every way we are like to ſuffer, not only by himſelf, but alſo by the Fox, who is now ſo much his Intimate, as he can cruſh us at pleaſure; and when we would complain, the Fox perhaps will take our Petition, but the King ſhall never ſee it. Having thus reaſoned, they ſate ſilent for ſome time, until at length the Cat, with a courage undaunted, thus ſpake. Noble Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> you are mighty, and I am crafty; it is not to be doubted, but if you and I agree together, we may acquit our ſelves of this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Well ſaid Couſin <hi>Tibert,</hi> quoth the Bear; if you can propoſe the way, I will endeavour to follow your propoſal. Why Sir, ſaid the Cat, the way I would have you take, is this, go unto Sir <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> and congratulate his happy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, expreſſing as great joy and affection as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then invite him to your Caſtle to dinner, and when he hath dinned (for I know he will eat ſo long, as until he is ſcarce able to ſtir) invite him to walk (telling him it is for his health) out into the Foreſt, where when you have him in a convenient place, fall upon him and tare him to pieces. Oh, Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> ſaid the Bear, I am fraid to ſet upon him alone, for he is devilliſh fierce, and for all that I know may
<pb facs="tcp:64820:14"/> kill me. Good Uncle, ſaid the Cat, fear him not, I <hi>will</hi> follow cloſe after you, and when you have got him down, I will tare out his throat I'le warrant you. Well then, ſaid the Bear, if you will be as good as your word, follow me, I will go to Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> preſently. So they both haſted, and got to the Wolfs houſe in a ſhort ſpace. When they were thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Evil men once advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally hated of their friends, becauſe they alſo ſee no ho hopes of ſharing with them in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; but if once they ſee a probability of their own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, they flatter, and baſely crouch to thoſe, whom they juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would have killed, as appears by this Chapter.</note> come, they found the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> and Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; for they were diſcourſing about ſeveral weighty matters. The Fox obſerving the countenance of theſe two Gueſts to be filled with hatred, howſoever they covered the ſame with a diſſembled cheerfulneſs; began to ſpeak to them in this manner: Noble Friends, had I not been engaged here with my Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> (for ſo his Majeſty will have him called ever after) I had ere this time ſent for you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with his Majeſties royal intention concerning you both; for ſo ſoon as this great Convention is over, which now will be (as you very well know) the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to morrow, our puiſſant King royally intends to honour you Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> with the Earldom of the Foreſts, an honour which the greateſt of Subjects muſt needs hold himſelf well contented with. And for you Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> he intends to make you Steward of his houſe; and if that like you not, he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to command the Earl of <hi>Pitwood,</hi> here preſent, to admit you for his principal Secretary, a place of unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able profit undoubtedly. When the Bear and the Cat heard ſuch mountains of Honour and Profit were like to fall in their Laps, and that ſo ſuddenly; their countenances and intentions were quite altered, and they with all due rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſaluted and honoured the Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> calling him the honourble Lord chief Prelate; and for the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> they told his Lordſhip they ſhould never be able ſufficiently to trumpet out his Praiſes, who had ſo highly promoted his Enemies in an extraordinary manner. After this they took their leaves, and departed far more ſecond than they came.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Aſſembly of the Commons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d what paſſed there.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>Then <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, roſe up, and after he had with a great ſhew of courteſie, bowed himſelf to the Aſſembly, he began to ſpeak thus. Worthy Sirs, his Majeſty our Royal King, taking care of the well-being of all his Subjects in general, could not without grief think of the ſad and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:64820:16"/> ſtate you all have been left in ſince the Death (<note n="*" place="margin">The true Emblem of an Hypocrite.</note> grieves me to ſpeak it!) of <hi>Bellin,</hi> and downfall of his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; therefore he in his Princely wiſdom for Princes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are far wiſer then their Subjects) hath thought of a moſt excellent expedient to prevent the enormities you were too-too apt to run into, for want of Teachers and Guides to direct you better: Therefore he adviſed with this incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably learned Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> requeſting as far as beſeemeth the Majeſty of a King to requeſt him, for the good of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all his liege people, to improve his great Learning to the general good of us all. This Noble Lord, was ſo far from excuſing himſelf, and avoiding, or ſhunning this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſome office, as he readily and cheerfully accepts of the ſame, and not only ſo, but alſo promiſeth to engage all his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neage (little leſs learned than himſelf) in the ſame Offices and Employments. We the Lords, being then all preſent and ſetting in Councel by his Majeſties command, ſeeing his great readineſs and alacrity, and alſo knowing how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent it would be to the well being of all, could not chuſe, but (by our joint conſent) vote him to be the Lord chief Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late throughout all his Majeſties Dominions. Thus was he, not without mature deliberation, choſen by us, and the choice confirmed by the King himſelf.</p>
               <p>Before he had ended theſe words, there was heard a rumor among the multitude, which at length grew louder and lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <note place="margin">Miſtakes in a multitude, do ſometimes give oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to the Judicious, of making their minds known.</note> Then the Fox feared ſome one or other had deſcried the falſe mask he (with his greateſt cunning) had put upon the buſineſs. But, after ſilence was commanded, it proved not altogether ſo. For among thoſe who ſtood furtheſt from the Scaffold, there were ſome who asked, what Lord that was that then ſpake? which queſtion made the greateſt part of the By-ſtanders to laugh, ſuppoſing it not poſſible for any of the Company not to know the Fox. This noiſe being heard among them by others that ſtood farther off, made them alſo to ask one another, what the noiſe meaned; they that ſtood neareſt the Scaffold were moſt of them <hi>Bellin</hi>'s friends, who had placed themſelves there, on purpoſe the
<pb facs="tcp:64820:17"/> better to deſcry the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi>'s perſon (as he was called) <note place="margin">Subtil Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they fear a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their falſe Paints and Diſguiſes, immediately betake them ſelves to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſmooth words full of guile.</note> whom they plainly knew to be <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf; therefore preſently, being asked by the Crier, what the noiſe meant? they ſaid, the Company behind deſired to know of what Country the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> was, ſome of them ſuppoſing, others affirming they had never ſeen him before, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were not willing to have a ſtranger impoſed upon them. The Fox hearing this, again bowed himſelf to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſaid: Loving Friends, and fellow Subjects, I marvel not, that it is ſuppoſed by ſome, and believed by others, that this honourable Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> here preſent, is a ſtranger or foreigner; becauſe he indeed all his life-time, with his whole Family and Lineage, hath lived a life ſo obſcure and ſecret, as never did any Monk in a Cloyſter live more retired; beſides he is ſo holy and debout, as the like of him is not to be found in the whole World: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he is ſo ſilent, and of ſo few words, ſo humble gentle, affable and kind, as I know not whether any mortal wight living may be compared unto him. And that is the reaſon he is ſo little known; for had be diſcovered himſelf before the King by his Princely Wiſdom took notice of him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly <note place="margin">The moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant moſt readily aſſent to, what they underſtand not.</note> none of you would in the leaſt have ſuſpected him to be a ſtranger: But this your ſuſpition had indeed ground enough, therefore his Majeſty is not in the leaſt offended with you, but wills that you give your Approbation by holding up your right Hands.</p>
               <p>Then the greateſt part of the Aſſembly held up their right hands, and many that ſcarce heard what was ſaid held up both. After this, <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf and his Linage bowed themſelves to the Company, but ſpake not a word, leaſt their Teeth ſhould be ſeen.</p>
               <p>When this was done, the King willed the Fox to ſpeak to the Aſſembly (before they were diſmiſſed) about <hi>Pitwood</hi>'s Linage. Therefore the Fox ſtanding up again, ſaid, His Majeſty is highly pleaſed with this your Approbation, and commanded me to thank you all: His <hi>further</hi> pleaſure is, that the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi>'s Linage be recommended to you for
<pb facs="tcp:64820:17"/> you aſſent for confirming their Offices under himſelf, now Lord chief Prelate; as to theſe perſons, in declaring the worth and goodneſs of their Father, I have not detracted any thing from them; for they all have led the ſame life with him, have béen always under his Tutelage, and ſtill will be under his Governance; ſo, as although any of them ſhould by reaſon of his Youth err, yet his Father will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſpy it and reclaim him; therefore I think you cannot do better for your ſelves, nor better pleaſe the King's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, than to diſcover your aſſent by holding up your hands. Then, as before, the greateſt part held up their hands; and <hi>Pitwood</hi> and his Lineage alſo bowed themſelves again, but ſpake not. When this buſineſs was ſo well effected to the great content of the King and Nobles but eſpecially of the Fox and Wolf; It was thought convenient to diſmiſs the Commons. Therefore <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock was commanded to intimate ſo much to them, which very formally he did; firſt by thrée <hi>O yes's</hi> commanding ſilence, afterward by ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the Aſſembly in this manner.</p>
               <p>Our Puiſſant King and all his Nobles give great thanks to you all, for your ſo re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy attendance this day, and alſo for that you have ſo chearfully aſſented to what was propoſed; therefore for your better commodity, and that you may with greater eaſe journey to your own homes, his Royal Majeſty and all his noble Lords here preſent have commanded me to diſmiſs you, and you are diſmiſſed for this time. Vpon this the Aſſembly brake up, ſome greatly contented, others doubtful, and not a few plainly ſorrowful for what had paſſed. When the Field began to be emptyed, and it was thought there was way enough for the King and his Nobles to walk to the Palace: The King firſt deſcended, after him <note place="margin">Knaves and Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l; (the firſt for ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, the laſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> imitation) honour the worthy, and moſt wicked</note> the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> then the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> and his Lineage, with ſuch ſeeming ſoberneſs, as many of the Commons that ſtayed to ſee the fight, admired the gravity of him and his. The Fox obſerving the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> was gazed upon, ſtept a little back. and walked directly before him bare-headed: the Bear and Cat ſeeing this, placed themſelves on each
<pb facs="tcp:64820:18"/> ſide of him. likewiſe bare headed; after him followed his Lineage all in order, and after them the Nobles, and laſtly <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Breck, leading a great Treop of Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vitors, that attended on the King and Nobles. In this Equipage marched they, till the King was ready to enter his own Palace; then did the Trumpets ſound, and all manner of other Muſick was heard in a melodious manner, conſtantly playing until all the whole company was entred the Royal Palace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King invited his Nobles the next day to a Feaſt, and what pafled thereat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen all the Nobles and their Followers were entred the Palace, the King willed them all to ſit down, and told them, the buſineſs of the day holding ſo long, and the iſſue alſo of the ſame being dubious, he would not reſolve what to do; but now his affairs being ſetled according to his wiſh, he deſired they would all accompany him on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at a Feaſt which ſhould be prepated for them; and then he would further declare his mind. They hearing this, all took their leaves and departed, every one to his own home.</p>
               <p>In the mean while the King ſent out his Purveyors into all parts, who provided ſtore of Veniſon, and other Cates in abundance. When the morrow was come, and noon drew nigh they all came much about one time: and after obeyſance made, all took their places at the Table, the Fox ſitting down on the right hand of the King, and the Wolf on his left, and all the other Nobles in order, giving place ſtill to <hi>Pitwood's</hi> Lineage; ſo as they ſate all intermixt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. When they were all ſate, the Servitors brought in Meat, dreſſed in divers manners with curious Sauces, and ſet it before them. Grace being ended, the King cuts firſt of the Diſh that ſtood neareſt him, bidding his Gueſts to fall to. They all in like manner lay hands of what was
<pb facs="tcp:64820:18"/> neareſt them, and ſoon made a clear board. Then thoſe empty platters removed, other full Diſhes, provided for a ſecond courſe, were ſet on the Table; while this was doing the King calls to his Servitors for Wine, which was brought, and the Cup given into the Kings hand, he drank to all his Gueſts, bidding them welcome, withal comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to fill unto every one that ſate at the Table. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done they fall to the ſecond courſe, and then began to talk a little. The Servitors fearing by their eating ſo much <note place="margin">Gluttons will always eat greedily, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ting at the Table of a King.</note> none would be left for them, take away the ſecond courſe, and bring in the third without bidding; and as before fill Wine to the King firſt, and afterward to the whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And this order they kept in all the following courſes till the Feaſt was done. Now when the Feaſt was ended, the King and all the Company looked very chearfully one upon another, and the King firſt of all ſaid. How bravely did our Couſin <hi>Reynard</hi> manage his buſineſs yeſterday? To this the Wolf (who during the Feaſt had ſaid nothing, leaſt his Téeth ſhould be ſéen too plainly by the Servitors) reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he did indeed (moſt Puiſſant Prince) act no otherwiſe, then as if he had been inſpired by an Oracle; in truth I was afraid all would not be well when that rumour and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring noiſe was heard among the Commons. That verily put me alſo to a ſtand, ſaid the For, and I was a little troubled till I heard what the matter was; then I knew I was able to put an end to that murmuring. I am glad all things are ſo well, ſaid the King; it will be our parts now to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <note place="margin">It is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in a King to give good Counſell, but it is baſeneſs in a Subject not to regard the ſame; as this Chapter, and the whole Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry following, clearly prove; for although here the Wolf for himſelf, by his ſilence, and the Fox for him, by a long and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, ſolomnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, or adviſed to, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them ever in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame.</note> to keep them ſo. Therefore to you my Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> I now ſpeak: I hope the Honour we have conferred on you and yours here preſent, will never be forgot; for whoſoever is unmindful of benefits, deviates from all honeſty. Our Subjects are numerous, and all of them (as I well noted) did not conſent to your Approbation, though the major part (which is ſufficient) indeed did very cheerfully. For this cauſe I would have you to conſider you have Enemies as well as Friends, which will be apt to eſpy all advantages, and ready to exclaim againſt you ſo ſoon as they can find any
<pb facs="tcp:64820:19"/> occaſion, which will by nothing be ſooner given, than by pride and licentious living; of which (though I thus ſpeak) I hope I ſhall have no occaſion to be jealous.</p>
               <p>Then ſtood up <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, and ſaid, Moſt dread Sovereign. I dare engage my honour, yea life and all, for the good deportment of my Uncle. For the reaſon why he heretofore was reputed churliſh, and licentious, was becauſe of his penury; this now being totally removed by the office your Majeſty hath given him, can be no cauſe of ſtirring up in him ſuch vices as were (in times paſt) condemnable in him: becauſe had he now no other eſtate to live on than his profits, (not to mention other Perquiſites) he muſt needs have ſo ample a competency, as that he ſhall need to deſire no more. Yea, I ſay, his riches will be ſo great, as he will be in a capacity rather to give to others, than to need any thing more than what his office daily ſupplies him with. Beſides, I conſider him by my ſelf; it is well known to your Majeſty, how I was continually complained of by my Enemies, accuſed of Murder, Theft and Rapine (as my former troubles do well witneſs) untill your Majeſty was pleaſed to advance me, and conſer on me ſo ample Treaſures, as I now poſſeſs. Since this time, not one Beaſt of all your Majeſty's Subjects hath ſo much as opened his mouth againſt me. It is true, <hi>Reynard,</hi> ſaid the King, I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard any complaint of thee ſince the time I firſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thee; therefore I repent me not of what I have done. Then the Fox bowing himſelf, ſaid I humbly thank your Majeſty for all your Favours beſtowed on me, as alſo for this great Bounty, for my ſake, conferred on my Uncle; of whom (doubtleſs) from this day forward, you will never more hear complaint. With this ſpeech of <hi>Reynards</hi> the King was greatly ſatisfied; and therefore ſaid, Couſin <hi>Reynard.</hi> I believe no leſs than you have told me. I am glad to ſee you affectionate and loving to your Uncle; I doubt not but he will repay your Kindneſs with like love and affection, and in the Execution of his office be always mindful of ſaving our Honour. Yes, ſaid <hi>Reynard,</hi> that will be his only aim; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64820:19"/> he hath already promiſed to be always more mindful of your Majeſties intereſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of his own. Theſe, and many more ſuch ſpeeches paſſed between the King and the Fox, until it was ſomewhat late in the Evening; then the King finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſcourz, told all his Gueſts it was late, he would detain them no longer. So they departed; only <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox was ordred to come to Court early in the morning; for the King told him he would ſpeak with him alone about earneſt Buſineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Diſcourſe the King had with <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox, touching the Advancement of Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear, and <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe</hi> day no ſooner appeared, but <hi>Reynard</hi> haſted to the Court; where his Majeſty had expected his coming al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an hour before, for he was troubled about his promiſe to <hi>Bruin</hi> and <hi>Tibert</hi> not yet performed, leſt they through diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content ſhould be the Authors of Commotion. Therefore, ſo ſoon as <hi>Reynard</hi> came in, he ſaid, it is well you are come, Couſin, I was even now, and indeed laſt night, thinking of my promiſe to <hi>Bruin,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Tibert,</hi> how remiſs I have been in performing my word, doubting whether by that omiſſion they two being diſcontented (as I ſuppoſe they are) might not raiſe ſome Commotion and ſtir among our Friends and Subjects. Hereupon, the Fox (now finding all things to ſucceed according to his own deſire) after obeyſance made, thus ſpeaks:</p>
               <p>Sure, mighty Prince, you have conſulted with the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, otherwiſe you could not have conjectured ſo truly. For <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear, and <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat were highly offended with my Uncle two days before the Aſſemby of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and came with full intent to his houſe to have done him ſome miſchief; but by good fortune, I being preſent, diſcerned their deſign by their looks, and therefore preſently told them of your Majeſty's royal intent to promote and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:64820:20"/> them, the very next day after the Aſſembly of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was over, which for the preſent pacifted them, very wolf, but ſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the time appointed is paſt and gone, without any effect, anſwerable to what I promiſed, how they now ſtand affected. I cannot tell. Well then, ſaid the King, I underſtand by your words, that it is high time to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in this buſineſs; but I pray thee Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> tell me which way I may beſt honour them, with leaſt damage to my ſelf, or injury to you. The Fox hearing this, after low Obeyſance made, ſaid; Dread Sovereign, if my poor judgment may be received in this caſe, I humbly requeſt your Majeſty to conſider the nature and temper of them both, and accordingly to honour them. To this the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, you ſpeak well Couſin, but ſince you beſt know their natures, I leave it to you to propoſe, which way they may be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be honoured?</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>The Fox hearing this, bowed his head, and departed full of joy and content; but forgot not to ſend in <hi>Tibert</hi> to the King. Now when <hi>Tibert</hi> came before the King, the King ſaid, Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> our will is, that you ſummon the Lords to
<pb facs="tcp:64820:21"/> be all here too morrow morning, for I purpoſe to confer Honours on Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> and your ſelf, of which I would have them to be witneſſes; alſo for the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi>'s good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, I intend, and fully reſolve to make him chief Baily of all my Dominions, therefore haſt you, and diſpatch your Buſineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox, Bear, and Cat, were honoured by the King; and how the Bear and Fox ſwore fealty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe</hi> Cat above meaſure joyed at this news, runs firſt to <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear, and acquaints him with the whole ſtory; then he haſtens to all the other Lords, and laſt of all comes to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> where <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Caſtle ſtood, into which he enters, and not finding <hi>Reynard</hi> at home, (for he was gone forth to hunt) he ſaluted <hi>Reynard</hi>'sWife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, (who were moſt of them of good ſtature) in theſe words: Reverend Madam, and you noble Lords, I am hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent by the Kings Royal Majeſty, to ſummon my Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> to the Court early on the morrow. Having ſaid this, away he runs to his own dwelling, and there remained until morning. Now, the morrow being come, and the Lords all preſent in the Court, the King ſitting down among them, began his diſcourſe thus.</p>
               <p>My Lords and Friends, We have done much toward the ſetling of our affairs in the choice and confirmation of the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> in his office of chief Prelate; yet there ſeems ſomething more of neceſſity to be done; for Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> hath béen long our leige-man, and although of ſo high deſcent, as you all know we have none nearer us by birth, except our own family, in all our Dominions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet we have never unto this day conferred on him any ſingular ſpecimen of honour. Therefore our will and pleaſure now is, before you all, to create him Earl of the Foreſts, thereby to oblige him nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to us, and to intimate to all our Subjects in general, that
<pb facs="tcp:64820:22"/> we will honour as many, as either by birth, or deſert, ought to be honoured. Alſo our will is, that Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> for his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente in executing our commands, be admitted by my Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> here preſent, as his chief Clerk. We know he is able and capable of ſuch an Imployment; therefore my Lord (directing his ſpeech to the Wolf) I pray accept of him as your Secretary, by me recommended. To this the Wolf replied, your Majeſty may command much more than this: I do here in this noble preſence accept of Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> as my chief Secretar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and none other. Then the King further ſaid, We have great reaſon to honour thoſe eſpecially, who (if at any time ſeeing us remiſs) admoniſh us of our duty, therefore I am now fully reſolved to confer greater honour on our Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> the Preſerver of our Royal Crown and Dignity<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Having ſaid this, he immediately before them all called to him the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> and when he had kiſſed him, gave him a ſtaffe headed with Gold; ſaying, this is our badg of honour, at all times to be born before you, by your Couſin <hi>Grimbard;</hi> or in caſe he be not well at any time, then by your Couſin <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>clas</hi> the Ape, ſo ſoon as he returns from <hi>Rome,</hi> whence he is hourly expected; and with this Staffe we give you power over all our Subjects, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute you Lord chief Baily of all our Dominions. After the King had ſpoke this, the Fox bowing himſelf, ſaid, Dread Soveraign, I ſhall never be able ſufficiently by words to expreſs my thankfulneſs, being wholly overcome by your Majeſties immenſe Bounty; but my Actions ſhall teſtifie my gratitude, to all your Subjects. Then the King, nodding his head and ſmiling, ſaid nothing to him, but called Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> and ſaid; Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> I create you Earl of the Foreſts, and if hereafter I have ſo ample a teſtimony of your Loyalty, as I at this time perſwade my ſelf I ſhall, I will confirm the ſame honour on your Heirs and Succeſſors for ever. The Bear hearing this, made obeyſance and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y thanked his Majeſty. To this the King ſaid, he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ewiſe to be thankful to his Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this great honour for him. Then the Bear turned
<pb facs="tcp:64820:22"/> himſelf, and gave the Fox great thanks alſo. This being <note place="margin">Oathes taken by wicked Perſons, are no longer binding to them, than till they can ſee an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying the ſame, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their ambitious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, as by the following ſtory is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Fox, and Bear, now ſworn before the King.</note> done, the King ſaid, now there remains nothing, but that you two ſwear Fealty to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors. Then the Wolf (whoſe office it was to ſwear them) gave them the Book, on which he bade each of them to lay his right hand, and then ſay after him: So the Fox and Bear after him repeated theſe words: We ſwear to be true and faithful to our Soveraign Lord the King, and directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly to practice nothing againſt his Royal Crown and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Having ſaid this, he bad them kiſs the Book, ſo they did, and then roſe up; for they took their Oath kneeling.</p>
               <p>This being done, the King diſmiſſed all his Nobles; and to the Fox particularly ſaid; Now, my Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> ſee that you deal juſtly to all my Subjects, in deciding their cauſes impartially; for I am willing you ſhould your ſelf redreſs the Grievances of my meaner Subjects; and what difference ſhall ariſe among you my Nobles and Friends, of that I my ſelf will have the Deciſion. Then the Fox bowed himſelf, and ſaid, All your Majeſties commands ſhall be exactly obeye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by me your moſt obliged.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Grimbard</hi> the Brock, receiving the Staff of <hi>Reynard,</hi> bore it before him; and <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf, <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear, and all the other Nobles followed after, and attended the Fox to his own Caſtle gates, where they took their leaves of him, and returned every one to his own home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf went to <hi>Malepardus</hi> to commune and adviſe with his Couſin <hi>Reynard</hi> about his own Affairs, and what was the Reſult of that Diſcourſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter this, ſome-time being elapſed, <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf, thought it neceſſary to go to his Couſin <hi>Reynard.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore coming to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> he knocked, and one of <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Sons roming to the gate, opened it, and bowed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> ſaying, My Father is within; if your Lordſhip would ſpeak with him. I will go in and call him. I pray thee do, ſaid the Wolf for I come for that end. So <hi>Reynards</hi> Son told his Father, the Lord chief Prelate was come to ſpeak with him. He hearing this, haſted to the Gate, and there ſaluted his Uncle, in theſe words, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Uncle I joy to ſee you, I think it not expedient to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite your Lordſhip to come into my Houſe, therefore we (going to younder hedg) ſhall have a very convenient place to ſit down and talk together; for I know we ſhall there have more privacy, then we can have within doors. Honourable Couſin ſaid the Wolf, I am always obliged to you for your readineſs to ſerve me, but eſpecially for your providence and forecaſt; your ſelf being ſo circumſpect and wiſe, as to be able to foreſee conveniency, or inconveniency, as oft as need is. By this time they were come to the Hedg, where the Fox ſitting down firſt, invited his Uncle to ſet by him. When he was ſat, the Fox began thus; Uncle <hi>Pitwood,</hi> I ſuppoſe by this time you perceive the profits of your office? Yes Couſin, ſaid the Wolf, I have indeed reaped no ſmall benefit by my office, the Perquiſites are large, and I have received great preſents, and thoſe of ſo great variety, as I never in all my life ſaw the like; beſides, there quantity is ſo great, as my own Houſe will hardly contain them. I am glad to hear it, ſaid the Fox; but how fares it with all my Couſins, your Children and Nephews, do they alſo thrive in
<pb facs="tcp:64820:23"/> their offices? Yes, very well, ſaid the Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> they tell me they have enough, and I believe them; for three or four of them have lately taken Surfeits with eating (poor hearts.) O Uncle ſaid the Fox, that's nothing, perhaps their Stomachs were weak; but they will be well enough in a little time. Yes, yes, Couſin, ſaid the Wolf, I doubt it not. But good Couſin, let me have your advice in ſome few things. Suppoſe I have more than I can tell where to beſtow, what ſhall I do with the remainder? ſhall I give it to the King, <note place="margin">This Chapter ſhews that Liberality is one main up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of Greatneſs, &amp; that without it, Envy and Malice may ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar prevail as to be able to ſhake, if not totally to ruin theſe that are in great honour and yet very c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vetous: Beſides, gifts blind the eyes and alter the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, as men are eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of that now, which they the day before did contemn as monſtrous.</note> or build my Houſe larger to receive all that comes, and your advice, ſhall I give to the King, and ſo ingratiate my ſelf further with him? Not ſo, ſaid the Fox, for the King ſeeing your great affluence of Riches, will begin to cut ſhort your other Revenues; ſuppoſing you will in time grow too mighty for him. That's very conſiderable, quoth the Wolf; what then? I perceive you allow of enlarging my houſe? No, ſaid the Fox, if you will take my advice, I ſee no ſecurity in that, but would rather perſwade you to inrich your Friends. How ſay you! what Friends can I have in this high eſtate, which every one envies? To this the Fox anſwers Uncle, did you ever know any one envied for giving? It is not your high eſtate that cauſeth envy; but the hatred of others againſt you, is becauſe they can reap no benefit by your greatneſs: Therefore, you cannot do better for your ſelf, nor better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your own Grandeur than by pleaſuring ſome few of the Nobles with a ſmall part of your wealth, now and then. Well Couſin, ſaid the Wolf, I will do ſo, but you muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe me to whom; for I know not what to do in ſuch a caſe as this? What to do, ſaid the Fox, why know you not that the Earl of the Foreſts, although mighty to ſée to, is but poor; and though he as yet carry fare to you and me, yet if he partake not of part of our Wealth he may in time prove a bitter enemy: Likewiſe Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, and <hi>Sly-look</hi> the Panther, are eſteemed great, yet we well know that ſome ſmall pittance from us, will be ſo thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by them, as we ſhall ever after oblige them firmly to
<pb facs="tcp:64820:24"/> us. And Uncle, it is a very neceſſary point to be thought on; for if we be diligent in obliging Friends ſo mighty, what is it we may not do? Yet you muſt be ſure to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of your own Servitors that they may not repine at your wealth; eſpecially, look into your Secretaries profits; if they be not large enough to content him, you muſt add more, till he holds himſelf well contented. For he who would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the greatneſs he at preſent hath, muſt not forget to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Attendants ſo, as they never utter one word in his diſcommendation. Couſin, ſaid the Wolf, I well underſtand you, and purpoſe to put in practice what you have adviſed. So for that time they parted, and the Wolf diſtributed his Goods among the before-recited Nobles, as freely and as liberally as ever Wolf did. And the Fox according to the advice he had given himſelf. did alſo largely reward thoſe of whom he thought he ſtood in greateſt need, or in time to come might have occaſion to uſe, and in his bounty exceeded the Wolf by far.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox behaved himſelf in his Office, and of two Cauſes by him decided.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Fox (who knew it was no leſs wiſdom to keep what is gotten, than to get the ſame) notwithſtanding his other affairs, (which now by reaſon of his Office were many) waits and tends upon the King as formerly, always making great Proteſtations of his Loyalty, touching which the King doubted not at all, the Fox had ſo craftily inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated himſelf into his affections. All being well on this ſide, we now come to ſpeak of his Deciſion of Cauſes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt differences among the meaner ſort of Subjects: And of theſe at this time we mention only two.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>After this there happened a great difference betwéen cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Daws and Rooks. The occaſion take as follows. In an high Tower, appert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ining to a Country-Town, where men formerly had dwelt, a company of Dawes took up their habitations, and had dwelt there ſo long as until they became very numerous. Right againſt this Tower, wère planted Elmes, which in length of time were grown up to a very great height; in the upper part of which, at firſt a few, and afterwards many Rocks but<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſetled their. Theſe two kinds kinds being ſo near N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighbou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, at length grew into acquaintance, and familiarity one with another: the Rooks pretending great kindneſs to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes, were by them admitted into their Houſes, and ſometimes feaſted; the Rooks likewiſe invited th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Daws to them, feaſting them after the ſame manner. This reciprocal entertainment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a long time, until a ſcarce and hard Seaſon came. Then the Rooks watching their opportunity, when the old Dawes were gone forth, (for it was Spring-time, and they had young ones) being greatly preſſed with hunger, agreed all together to rob the Dawes, and fearing the noiſe of the young Dawes would bewray their intentions, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved among them, firſt to kill all they found in every houſe. With this reſolution they all at once flew out, and one or two of them went into every houſe and ſlew all the young ones, ſome of which in carrying out they let fall, by reaſon of their haſte; but as many as they could hold, they carryed into their own Neſts, and returned immediately and took away all the Proviſions they could find (which was not much by reaſon of the ſcarcity of the time) and carryed that home alſo. Then with ſpeed ſome of them flew out to purvey, as at other times, but (by reaſon of their own hunger) m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de haſte home. By this time were the old Dawes alſo returned with proviſion for their Young, whom they never more ſaw alive. Therefore ſmelling the deceit, ſome of the boldeſt of them flew over to their Neighbours, and coming unawares
<pb facs="tcp:64820:26"/> upon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, could eaſily ſee the torn limbs of their children. Others of them flying again downwards, eſpied under the Tower-walls ſeveral of their younglings lying dead. At this, they were all ſo much enraged, as had not ſome of the wiſeſt among them diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aded them from it, they would have ſuddenly in an hoſtile manner aſſailed their Enemies. Therefore they took up this reſolution, namely, that they would complain of their Grievances to the King of Beaſts. But after it was told them that the King himſelf would not meddle in their matters, becauſe he had deputed his Couſin <hi>Reynard,</hi> they all fly to him, and lighting on a Trée<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th the place of Iudicature, they called aloud, Iuſtice, Noble Lord <hi>Reynard. Reynard</hi> being informed of this Cry, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately came forth, and ſitting down, ſaid, What is the matter? They ſaid, my Lord, avenge our cauſe of thoſe perſidious Rooks, who have ſlain our Children and robbed us of all our ſubſtance. To this, the Fox replied, how ſhall I know your complaint is juſt, unleſs I alſo hear thoſe that be accuſed? At this, they all flew away home, and being there, called to their Neighbours the Rooks, telling them they muſt appear before the Lord <hi>Reynard.</hi> To this the Rooks anſwered, that was no lawful Summons; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, they would not ſtick to appear, being ſufficiently able to clear themſelves. So ſome of the oldeſt of the Rooks flew firſt to the Court of Iudicature; the Daws ſeeing that, made haſte after them. When both had lighted on Trees as near the Foxes ſeat, as they could, the Dawes as before, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit their complaint. To this the Rooks anſwer, My Lord, theſe Dawes here preſent, belye us ſhrewdly; for we as well as they were gone forth to purvey for Neceſſaries; but their young ones intheir abſence crawled out, and fell down, and ſo died; ſome of which are to be ſeen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at this preſent, broken to pieces againſt the Stones; and this is the cauſe why theſe Varlets accuſe us, who are as innocent as your Lordſhip. To this the Fox anſwered, it is ſtrange that all the young ones in every houſe ſhould at one time be alike diſpoſed to crawl out; I ſuſpect the truth of this matter, and cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit
<pb facs="tcp:64820:26"/> you, unleſs you can by ſubſtantial Witneſſes, evidence the truth of your Aſſertion. Then the oldeſt of the Rooks ſaid, My Lord we are able to produce Witneſſes enough, ſome of which ſaw this downfall of the young Dawes. Go to then, ſaid the Fox, produce them. Then haſted one or two of the Rooks, and in a ſhort time produced all the reſt of their <note place="margin">It is danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for guilty perſons to come within the Judg his power.</note> fellows, who had an hand in the former Maſſacre of the Dawes. When theſe Witneſſes were come, the Fox com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them down to be ſworn: Therefore down they came (though unwillingly) and after they were ſworn, and ready to give evidence, he would not hear them, before the other Rooks, who were accuſed, were alſo come down off the Trèes, and brought to the Bar. Now ſaid he to the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, let us hear what you can ſay. We, my Lord, ſaid one of them, were eye-witneſſes of what hapned to the young Dawes; for they came all to the doors of their houſes, and there looked one upon another, until at length, ſtriving (as it ſeems) to fly (before they were able) they all tumbled down headlong. Now indeed, we ſeeing they were fallen and dead, took up every-one of us one of them, and carried them home, becauſe we knew they were dead. When theſe our Kinsfolks, who are now arraigned, came home, we told them the whole ſtory; they allowed of what we had done; becauſe that was free booty, yet to avoid the ill-will of our Neighbours, they would not ſuffer us to fetch up any more of their dead bodies. Now it is true, that ſome of the Dawes flying over to us, did ſee many of us the Witneſſes eating of the dead bodies of their Children, and therefore without one word ſpeaking, they falſly affirmed to your Lordſhip that we had ſlain their children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and robbed them, So then ſaid the Fox, you deny you have robbed them, yet confeſs you eat the dead Younglings. Now where are ſtoln goods to be found, but in the poſſeſſion of the Thief? Therefore by your own evidence you have condemned your ſelves, and I can do no leſs in equity than to condemn you all to be ſtrangled, as a juſt recompence for your heinous Maſſacre. When he had ſaid this, the Fox's Attendants ſtrangled every one of them
<pb facs="tcp:64820:27"/> in a moments time; but their dead bodies were delivered <note place="margin">Crafty men willingly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give away what is not their own, nor ever like to be in their poſſeſſion, as here is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, by the Fox, who gives the Dawes the Rookes Neſts, becauſe he knew not how to come at them.</note> by T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le into the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Kitchin. The D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was done, rejoiced greatly, and bowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Fox, ſaid, Honoured Sir, we are infinitely
<pb facs="tcp:64820:27"/> bound to your Lordſhip, for that you have ſo juſtly avenged our cauſe on the Murtherers of our Children. The Fox anſwered, I could do no leſs; ſor I plainly perceived they were guilty, both of Murther and Theft; therefore I give you all the Houſes and Goods remaining of theſe Miſcreants, (although indeed my own Pexquiſites) that you may ever after live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſecure from ſuch treacherous Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Now when the Dawes had humbly thanked the Fox, they took their leaves and departed; and from that day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward would never after have any Fellowſhip with Rooks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox liberally beſtowed what he got, among the Nobles, and of the Communication that was held by them at a general Meeting.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Fox in this manner handling all matters ſo, as <note place="margin">When aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Subjects abound in Wealth, the Kings royal perſon and power is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to great danger.</note> which way ſoever the ſcale turned, profit ſhould redound to him, partly by Brides taken privily on both ſides, and partly by the Forfeitures of the condemned, had got together an infinite maſs of Wealth. Then knowing his own great Riches, he aſpired to advance his eſtate yet higher, yea even above his Maſter, that had honoured him ſo highly, and had given him power ſufficient to endanger his own Crown and Dignity. Therefore, to proceed ſurely (as he thought) to his before-imagined Grandeur, he ſhews himſelf much more liberal than formerly, enrighing all the Nobles, and their Followers and Retinue, among which he moſt of all gratified Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat, giving to him very largely. By this liberal giving, he was the only eminent perſon in the land (as they who were ſo greatly benefited by him judged) that was endued with Wiſdom, Policy, and great Riches. To <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf (though he had wealth enough of his own he alſo forgat not to ſend ſeveral Preſents, not once or twice, but oftner. He holding this courſe with the
<pb facs="tcp:64820:28"/> Nobles, was not in the mean while unmindful of waiting often on the King, and with ſmooth words, and a lying pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of honeſty, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull him aſleep even to a Lethargy of ſecurity; for the King being old, and hearing no complaints, was well pleaſed, that he had conſtituted a Subſtitute who was able and willing to free and diſcharge him of all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thus the Fox, concealing his intent, ſeemingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haded himſelf moſt uprightly and indeed he was ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect as he would never divulge his mind, until he ſaw a manifeſt occaſion offer it ſelf very plainly. Some time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed, the Nobles were all met together at the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi>'s houſe, to which Meeting the Fox came not, but attended on the King, whether neceſſitated thereunto, or purpoſely is not well known At this meeting, the Fox's great worth was highly magnified and <hi>Pitwood</hi> himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled him to the skies, adding withal, that he was fit to rule a Kingdom. Theſe words being minded by thoſe who judged all he ſaid to be true, ſpurred them on to ſpeak diſloyally of their Soveraign. Therefore <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uin</hi> the Bear broke his mind <note place="margin">Alſo the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſecurity is the diſloyal Subjects ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and whenſoever any man in power is magnified (by other potent men) above his Maſter, and the King his Maſter evil ſpoken of, actual Treaſon is ready to be produced, as this Chapter clearly ſhews.</note> thus. He is indeed a moſt worthy perſon, and is more mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to recompence and pleaſure his Friends, than the King himſelf; for what gives he to any of us? If we bring him Preſents, he for the preſent only thanks us, and afterward never more thinks of us, or our Preſent; but the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> expects no gifts from us, and yet is never weary of conferring Benefits on us. To this <hi>Bittelas</hi> the Ape aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented (for he was newly come from <hi>Rome)</hi> and ſaid, My Nephew the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> is not only wiſe, but courteous, affable, and exceeding mindful of Benefits; yea, and where he neither hath, nor can expect to have reaped any commodity, there alſo his benevolence is largely extended. It is true indeed, ſaid <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard; and his near Kinſman, <hi>Sly-look</hi> the Panther owned as much. At length one among them ſaid, if a vacancy ſhould happen, ſhall we not do well to elect <hi>Reynard</hi> for our lawful King? Yes, ſaid another, we may do well in ſo doing; but it is not time to talk of ſuch matters as yet. No, no, ſaid <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wlof,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:28"/> we ſhall endanger our Heads by ſuch a diſcourſe (as this) if it ſhould happen to come to the Kings ear. Beſides, for us to imagine ſuch a thing, before we conſult with the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> thereabout, to know whether he will accept of our good endeavours, and ſtand by us in it, and aſſiſt us with his wealth and friends, I judg it a very great imprudence, if not a raſh and hazardous folly.</p>
               <p>To theſe words of his, they all aſſented, and for that time ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke no more thereabout.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape informed <hi>Reynard</hi> of all that paſſed at the Meeting of the Lords.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON the morrow early, <hi>Bitleas</hi> the Ape journeyed to his Nephew <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Caſtle, and when he was let in he ſpake to the Fox in this manner:</p>
               <p>Honoured Nephew, I hear your commendations ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commemorated, as I am above meaſure joyed thereat. The Nobles are all at your devotion, there is not one of them, but he is ready to hazard Life and Fortune for your further advancement: You know my meaning Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, do you not? Yes Uncle, ſaid the Fox, I know it well enough; for I can ſtep but one ſtep higher, and I think it not time as yet to begin that Aſcent. No no, ſaid the Ape, you miſtake me Nephew, if you think I mention this to engage your Lordſhip into any raſh attempt but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that you knowing your Friends, may the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how to uſe them, when occaſion is. You ſpeak very well Uncle, ſaid the Fox. Will you do one thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or me? Yes, ſaid the Ape, that I will Couſin if poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. Then ſaid the Fox, go to every of the Lords apart, and ſound them, to ſée how they ſtand affected; and bring me an exect account.</p>
               <p>So the Ape with all diligence ſounded them, and found not one diſſenting, but largely promiſing to hazard all to
<pb facs="tcp:64820:29"/> inveſt the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> with Regal Power. Only he <note place="margin">As in all Treaſons, ſome one principal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Grand Proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, to ſound the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all the Conſpirators, ſo here the Ape is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the <hi>Fox</hi> to fathom the Affections and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all the other Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate. Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. This ſhews great craft in the Projector; for if any one had diſſented he then had a fair occaſion to accuſe all the other, and ſo clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> perceived that the Bear ſcrupled his Oath to the King; becauſe he ſaid If he were but abſolved there-from, he would be none of the backwardeſt to promote this deſign. All this he related to <hi>Reynard</hi> three days after. Then <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaid. ſmiling, Uncle you have done me a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I will repay it ere long. As for <hi>Bruin</hi>'s doubt, I can eaſily remove it; for I am ſure the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve both him and my ſelf from that Oath extorted from us by the King, ſo ſoon as time ſhall ſerve for effecting this buſineſs: Yet <hi>we</hi> muſt not only relie on the Favour of the Lords, but by the beſt means we can, engage the Commons alſo. It is true Nephew, ſaid the Ape; but how that will be done. I cannot tell; for if Soldiers ſhould be liſted, that would never be done ſo ſecretly, but it would be bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zed abroad, and ſo come eaſily to the King's ear. No Uncle, ſaid the For, that is not the <hi>way.</hi> We muſt proceed after another manner than vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to raiſe any Soldiers: Each Lord, muſt by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and reward engage as many of the Commons as he can, pretending a private Quarrel, in which he would have their aſſiſtance, and therefore injoyn them to be ready armed at any time, when he ſhall call.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Apt, admiring his Nephews Wiſdom, ſaid, This is the direct way to raiſe an Army inviſibly. To this the Fox ſaid, if we intend to effect our buſineſs throughly, we muſt not viſibly raiſe Soldiers until the hour appointed be fully come; then how ſquares will go we ſhall ſoon know; and if our firſt Exploit proſper, all the other will ſucceed accordingly, and we ſhall need the fewer Soldiers. Therefore the ſtreſs of all lies in managing the buſineſs well at firſt: If we miſcarry at firſt, our Deſign will ſcarcely be effected; ney, it is well if our own Ruin fall not in as an Appendix. The Ape hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, ſaid, <hi>You</hi> do well Couſin to promiſe the worſt; this ſeems to me a ſure preſage of the future Event, that
<pb facs="tcp:64820:29"/> it will be exceeding proſperous. Well Uncle, ſaid the Fox, if it proſper, and I obtain my deſired end, I will honour and reward you above all others.</p>
               <p>Thus did the Fox diſloyally intend the ruin of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, his greateſt friend, to whom he had ſolemnly ſworn fealty; but what ſucceſs he had, ſhall hereafter be ſhewed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Diſcourſe between the Fox and the Wolf, and of another Meeting of the Lords, and what was agreed on among them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Fox, now filled with hopes of obtaining the height of all power, reſolved to let paſs no opportunity of promoting his deſign; therefore, the firſt leiſure-time he had, he beſtowed in Conference with the Wolf. Who not only promiſed his Aſſiſtance, but alſo to abſolve him, and the Bear from their Oath of fidelity. Telling the Fox, that all the Lords he was ſure were like minded with him. If ſo, ſaid the Fox, it were neceſſary, loving Uncle, to ſummon the Lords as privately as may be. That is done already, ſaid the Wolf, and they will be all here by and by; but I willed the Meſſenger not to ſummon you, becauſe I intended ſo ſoon as they were all ſat down, to diſpatch an Herauld pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to you. This courſe I thought would be beſt, for who ſoever ſhould at that time have been with you, they would have judged, that the King was here, and ſo not have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered their ſervice to come and attend you hither, becauſe of the haſte all know you are wont to make when his Majeſty ſends.</p>
               <p>By this time, ſeveral of the Lords were come in, moſt of them entring through the back-gate, for fear of being ſuſpected Now as every one came in, he firſt ſaluted the Fox with great Reverence, then the chief Prelate <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> lately ſtiled <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>twood.</hi> When all were come, &amp; each ſate down orderly in his wonted place, <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf ſtood up,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:30"/> and bowing himſelf a little, ſaid, My Lords, here is now preſent the Noble and Puiſſant Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> of whom Fame hath made ſuch a loud report <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have diſcloſed your intentions to him, and he very well approving thereof, now gives you this meeting. Then the Fox ſtood up and ſaid, My Lords and loving Fridnds. I am not ignorant of your affectionate deſire to advance me yet one ſtep higher than I at preſent am. I alſo am informed that for effecting this, you will hazard Life and Fortune, (for which I give you great thanks, and will not fail to return a proportionable recompence, if ever I attain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wiſhed end) yet I cannot underſtand, you have to your ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> propoſed what way to take to bring about your purpoſe. Then Sir <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uin</hi> the Bear, lately made Earl of the Foreſts, ſaid, Noble Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> we are all ready to ſerve you, and follow the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections your Lordſhip ſhall think good to propoſe. The Fox hearing this, ſaid, he could propoſe an expedient courſe, which being taken, would further the deſign, and yet not be perceived; but before he did that, he deſired to be abſolved from the Oath of Fealty, which he and <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear ſwore to the King. The Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> hearing this, ſtood up and ſaid? I here abſolve you, Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> and you Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> of the Oath you have taken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and you are abſolved. After this, the bowing himſelf, began to ſpeak thus. Worthy Friends, it is well known unto us all, that we have need of the Commons; for as no man can work without hands, ſo we can never accompliſh what we intend, without the aſſiſtance of many more than we out ſelves are. Alſo for procuring their aſſiſtance we muſt not publickly invite, or ſolicite any, or otherwiſe hire and liſt, as is uſual in ſuch Caſes. Therefore there is but one way left us and that is beſt and will be moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. The way is this; Let every one of us here preſent, by promiſe and reward, oblige as many of the Commons as we can, telling them we require their aſſiſtance in a private quarrel, and therefore would have them be ready (but ſecretly) in Arms, till we do call for them: This
<pb facs="tcp:64820:30"/> way will both conceal our deſign and our ſelves, until we <note place="margin">Here it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that Flattery and Diſſimulation are neceſſary concomitants of Treaſon: for had not the Fox wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the King as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven cauſe of ſuſpition.</note> think good to diſcloſe our ſelves and it. The Nobles hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Foxes propoſal, approved thereof; and highly prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Wiſdom, ſaid, They would put in practiſe what he had ſo prudently adviſed to. Then he again ſtood up and ſaid, Worthy Friends, if you think good to put in practice our advice, we alſo judg it expedient, that all ſpeed poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble be uſed, becauſe delay may produce danger; and indeed ſuch deſigns as this ſhould be as ſoon executed as thought on. Therefore I requeſt you, and as Confederates adjure you to uſe all diligence this evening, and all day too mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to oblige as many as you can, and then to meet here to morrow-night, that we may determine what to do, and appoint the hour, in which we will ſet about the buſineſs, and diſpatch it.</p>
               <p>Having ſaid this, the Meeting broke up, and the Lords went forth one by one, as privily as they could.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of their laſt meeting, and how they determined to ſurpriſe the <note place="margin">Alſo Miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants before they attempt dangerous Deſignes, forecaſt how in ſecure themſelves if it happen their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons befruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as here is evident by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ox his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ortilying, and furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Caſtle to abide a ſiege, if need ſhould be.</note> King and Court the next night following.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe next day the Fex went to Court, and tarried with the King until Dinner-time; then with great ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and ſeeming Loyalty he took his leave of him; who doubting nothing, diſmiſſed the Fox with great chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Reynard</hi> came home, he was not idle, but ſtayed at home all that day, not only to view the Fortifications of his Caſtle, (for he under pretence of repairing it, had already fortified it ſtrongly) which he liked well, but alſo to examine his ſtores of Proviſion, obſerving what was deficient, and ſupplying the ſame that day, that if need were) he might abide a Siege to the confuſion of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as he ſtill ſtedfaſtly hoped. Therefore ſuch Soldiers
<pb facs="tcp:64820:31"/> as he levied privily, he kept there, with a plentiful allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of all that was needful.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look,</hi> revealed the whole Treaſon to the King, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON the morrow when Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin met, they both looked leſs theerful then they were wont; and therefore asked each other the cauſe of his ſadneſs. The Libbard firſt ſpake thus:</p>
               <p>Couſin, I am troubled with the thoughts of what we are going about; for I conſider we have no reaſon to be Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <note place="margin">Relenting thoughts in Conſpirators, prove dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to grand Projectors.</note> to our Soveraign, becauſe he never in the leaſt degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or injured us, but always admitted us as Friends and Companions; and indeed he is a Prince deſerving the love and not the hatred of all his Subjects, much more of his Lords, and in an eſpecial manner of the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> and his Uncle <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> ſince called <hi>Pitwood.</hi> But now engaged as we are, we are in ſuch a ſtreight as what to do I cannot tell.</p>
               <p>Then the Panther ſaid, Truly Couſin, I know not what to think, I have been ſo perplexed all this night with the conſideration of my Diſloyalty, as I am now even at my Wits end. If we bewray the Plot to the King, he is ſo well conceited of the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> as he will not believe us; and ſo we are in danger of death for falſly accuſing him, who is the falſeſt of all living, and will not ſtick to ruin all us, ſo he may but eſcape himſelf. Beſides, his language is ſo ſmooth, and he is ſo crafty and ſubtile as it will be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove a tittle of all we can ſay againſt him. No, no, ſaid the Libbard, if we having declared all to the King, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt him to detain us in his Court but for one day, until our Loyalty be proved or diſproved, and in the mean while not be known we have bewrayed the Plot; we when the time appointed is come, may look over the Battlements and call to Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> (who will be ſure to lie very near, that he may give intelligence) telling him the King and his Sons are
<pb facs="tcp:64820:33"/> dead, the Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> may now come in ſecurely; then we ſhall quickly ſée our ſelves out of danger, and the Authors of our trouble brought to condign puniſhment. Couſin, ſaid the Panther, I like your counſel well; but if we be detained in Court all day, and come not with our Soldiers in the Evening to the place of Rendezvouz, <hi>Reynard</hi> will preſently ſmell the matter, and let fall his preſent deſign, but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately run to Court and accuſe us. 'Tis true indéed, ſaid the Libbard, we are in a bad caſe if we reveal the Treaſon, and it is very hazardous if we reveal it not, and any other do; our danger will be the greater. Therefore, ſince we are ſo ſtraitned, it is better for us of theſe two Evils to chuſe the leaſt, and ſpeedily to reveal the Treaſon, let the event be what it will.</p>
               <p>To this the Panther conſented; and ſo they went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Court. When they were come before the King, and <note place="margin">This Chapter ſhews, that ſome men are eaſily wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſent to Treaſon, yet will very un willingly put the ſame in practice; but rather, to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, reveal the whole Conſpiracy, as here the Libbard and Panther did.</note> had vowed themſelves, they thought to have ſpoke, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them could for ſhame and grief. The King noting their dejected Countenances, ſaid, Friends, why are you ſo ſad? O Sir, ſaid the Libbard, the conſideration of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties clemency, and our own unworthineſs, is the cauſe of our preſent grief. Why (ſaid the King) ſpeak you thus; Becauſe Sir, ſaid the Panther, we have been ſo unworthy, and indeed ſo falſe to your Majeſty, as to know of a Treaſon (intended againſt your Royal Perſon, Crown and Dignity) for at leaſt four days, and not to reveal it; and that which moſt of all perplexeth us, is, that we gave our conſents, and promiſed to aid and aſſiſt the Traytors againſt your Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Here the King interrupted him; ſaying, Treaſon! and would have ſpoke more, but for rage could not ot preſent. Iu a little time his wrath abating, he ſternly ſaid, Who be the Traytors? At which words the Panther and Libbard trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled excéedingly, and ſaid, We he thoſe Traytors who diſſoyally conſpired your Majeſties Death. The King hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, knew not what to ſay, but ſuppoſed they were mad. Therefore he again asked them; What, do you accuſe your
<pb facs="tcp:64820:34"/> ſelves, are you Traytors? Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, we are, ſaid they. Then the King ſaid would you have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdon? Yes, ſaid they, if your Majeſty ſo pleaſe. Pleaſed I am to pardon all that of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves make complaint firſt; therefore I here pardon you, how ſoul ſoever the Treaſon be, provided you will reveal the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſpiracy, and Conſpirators. At theſe words they took courage, and (after Obeyſance) ſaid We will not only reveal the whole Treaſon exactly, from point to point as it is, but will alſo (if your Majeſty will act by our advice) deliver all, or moſt of the Traytors into your own hands, to deal with them as your Highneſs ſhall think fit. Well, ſaid the King, firſt let me know the Conſpiracy, and Conſpirators.</p>
               <p>So they in all points declared the whole Treaſon and Traytors, from beginning to end, as you have heard. Then the King ſaid, How ſay you, all the Lords! Yes, Sir, ſaid they from the higheſt to the loweſt, there was not one that co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſented not. It is true indeed Sir, <hi>Tibert</hi> was not at our Meetings, but he muſt needs be privy to it; for he is made Captain of the Scouts that are to go before the Army; and undoubtedly he may be ſeen in or about the Court this night, if a diligent ſearch be made for him. The King hearing this, was above meaſure troubled and would often have ſent for <hi>Reynard,</hi> had not his eldeſt Son, and his other Friends preſent, perſwaded him to the contrary; ſaying, We have often heard your Majeſty ſay, you have twice ſaved <hi>Reynard</hi> from death, and that his Loyalty of late had ſo far repaid the Recompence of all his former Miſdemeanors, that you had no cauſe to repent of all, or any your Favours. Hath it not been too, too often ſeen, that ſome who receive greateſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, are moſt ungrateful to their Benefactors? And is there not a Proverb, <hi>Save a Thief from the Gallows, he will hang you if he can?</hi> All this is true, ſaid the King, but ſure our Couſin <hi>Reynard</hi> is not a Traytor. To this, his Son and Friends ſaid, Sir, while your Majeſty is of this mind, the depth of this Treaſon can never be ſufficiently known; for if <hi>Reynard</hi> be ſent for, he will deny all, and (if he be guilty,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:34"/> as we believe he is) acenſe others moſt malielouſly, and ſo <note place="margin">A well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be perſwnded to entertain bad thoughts of any one, that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been his friend; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears here by the King, who would not believe that <hi>Reynard</hi> was a Traytor, &amp;c.</note> (if your Majeſty give credit to his words) eſcape himſelf, and another time put that in practice effectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly, which now (we have good reaſon to hope) he can never be able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh. With theſe and the like words, the King was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dr wn from his intent of ſending for <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox. Therefore he turning to the Panther and Libbard, ſaid: Which way can you enervate this Treaſon, and deliver the Traytors into our hands? They anſwered, My Lord we think it not poſſible to deliver <hi>Reynard</hi> himſelf, becauſe he already intends to come laſt; and in ſurpriſal of the other Lords, ſome one or other of <hi>Tiberts</hi> Lineage will enter in among them, and then ſeeing what is done, acquaint <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> therewith; but for moſt of the other Lords, we may make ſure of, before any thing of our intent is perceived, if <hi>Tibert,</hi> who will be ſure to come this night, enter not with us into Court, For if your Majeſty will be rightly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the effect, and be reſolved to take your Traytors acting their Treaſon, we muſt have leave to dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt and go to the place of Rendezvouz, at the time appointed to meet the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers by us levyed, which will be near Six hundred; with theſe Soldiers we (with your Majeſties leave) will enter the Court, and leaſt <hi>Tibert</hi> ſhould diſcover our intent, will counterfeit a fight, as againſt your Majeſties Guard, and then ruſhing in, will by and by cry, all is our own. When this is done, one of us will call to <hi>Tibert,</hi> and ſend him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, telling him we have ſlain all the Fox ordered ſhould be ſlain, and charge him to make haſte. Thus we ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh all things well; and undoubtedly, before intelligence can be given to <hi>Reynard,</hi> intangle moſt of the Nobles in their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Net.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Forces of the Lords met at the place appointed, and how <hi>Firrapel,</hi> and <hi>Sly-look</hi> entred the Court, and enſnared moſt of the Confederates, and among them <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIr <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, and <hi>Sly-look</hi> the Panther, were no ſooner gone from Court, but they haſted all they could to <hi>Reynard,</hi> who was at home waiting their coming; for the whole hindge of his buſineſs depended on their Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, how ſquares went at Court. When they came near his Caſtle, he came forth and met them, and ſaid, My noble Friends you are welcome, how is it you ſtayed ſo long? To this they anſwered, Moſt excellent Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> after we had ſpoke unto the King according to the Inſtructions we received from your ſelf; he entertained us with a large diſcourſe of your Merits, telling us how highly he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with your Lordſhips great diligence, by which he could <note place="margin">Here is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon repaid with Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</note> take his pleaſure without fear or care, adding many ſuch like expreſſions too long to be now recited; we were conſtrained to ſtay by this occaſion, otherwiſe we had waited on your Lordſhip ſooner. All is well, ſaid the Fox, you are come ſoon enough. I would have you now to mind your Levies, and ſee your Soldiers be all well armed. for fear of the worſt, becauſe you know, it is ordered that you give the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. To this they replied, My Lord, we are ready to obey your command, and ſo they departed about their Levies, but not with the ſame intent as <hi>Reynard</hi> ſuppoſed. So ſoon as it began to be dark, the Soldiers in Troops repaired to the Foreſt, where their Lords were ready to attend them; and when they were all come, they embatteled them as ſoon as was poſſible. <hi>Reynard's</hi> Eſpials giving him Intelligence they were all ready, he gave command for their March; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look</hi> marched out with their Six hundred Soldiers, having not many Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers out of the other Companies, becauſe each Lord ſtrove
<pb facs="tcp:64820:36"/> to have moſt Soldiers. <hi>Reynard</hi> met this Forlorn Hope, and ſaluted the Leaders very courteouſly. but ſpoke not loud. So on they march until they come to the Court-gates. When there, they ſtand a little, and make a pretended ſcuffle with the Kings Guard, who well know the Kings mind and ſo reſiſted but coldly. But before Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> was entred himſelf, he charged <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat to wait in one certain place without the gate that he might the better inform him how ſquares went; and he, when it was time to be gone, have no let; withal charging him to command his Soldiers to lie cloſe round about the Walls of the Court, that if called to on any ſide, they might preſently be ready to run and give intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. <hi>Tibert</hi> did as he was commanded Now, when Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look</hi> with all their Soldiers were entred, and had ſtayed within ſome ſmall time. Sir <hi>Firra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> failed not to call to <hi>Tibert</hi> aloud, ſaying, the day is our own haſte quickly and tell our Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> that all are dead whom he commanded ſhould be killed. <hi>Tibert</hi> hearing this, ſent two of his Soldiers to the Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> who was not far with the whole Army, to tell him the Newes; but ran himſelf to the Lord <hi>Reynard,</hi> and ſaid, Moſt noble Lord, your renowned Captains <hi>Firrapel,</hi> and <hi>Sly look,</hi> have fully executed your Lordſhips commands, and all your Enemies are dead; this they have me tell you. The Fox hearing this, ſaid, It is good news indeed, if it be true: True Sir, ſaid the Cat, I'le warrant you Nevertheleſs the Fox, like an old Soldier, would not believe the firſt report, but ſent away <note place="margin">Politick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons believe not reports by Hear-ſay, but require a Teſtimony from fight</note> Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> commanding him to enter into the Court, if poſſible, and then to tell him what he knew. In the mean while, <hi>Reynard</hi> commanded <hi>Pitwood</hi> the Wolf to march up to the Court-gates with the whole Army embattelled as they were, and then to make a ſtand, and call to him all the Commanders to adviſe what was fit to be done, ſtill (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) wiſhing him to proceed warily, and to be well infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, before he attempted any thing. But the Wolf, being over-credulous, and above meaſure joyful at the News he had heard, forgat all counſel of warineſs. Therefore, being
<pb facs="tcp:64820:36"/> come up, he found Sir <hi>Firrapel,</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look,</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding without the Court-gate, with all their Soldiers ready embattelled within. At this ſight, he was confirmed in his former conceit, and therefore ſtepping a little before the Army, he ſaluted them, congratulating their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſs. To this they anſwer, We indeed, noble <note place="margin">Covetous and greedy mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting all good &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſel given them, ruſh head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long upon their own ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, where matter of profit is ſtrewed as a bait.</note> Lord <hi>Pitwood,</hi> did at firſt find ſome reſiſtance, but our Soldiers couragiouſly fighting, ſoon overcame the Guard and then the King and his Friends were without difficulty diſpatched. Now my Lord, if it be your pleaſure to walk in, and if your Honour will ſend for all the Comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, we may the better conſult what is fit to be done within, when we are all together; and beſides here is ſtore of Proviſions, which were left of the Feaſt. Here the Wolf interrupted, Proviſions Sir, ſaid he! I am in truth very hungry, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving walked about all this night; and with theſe words proffered to go in. Then Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> ſaid I beſeech your Lordſhip firſt to command the Army to ſtand ſtill em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battelled as they are, and then to ſend for Sir <hi>Bruin,</hi> and our other noble Commanders; otherwiſe, if your Lordſhip only enter your ſelf, the other Lords will ſuſpect ſome Treaſon is plotted by us, and ſo an irrecoverable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction and danger will follow. It is well conſidered Sir <hi>Firrapel,</hi> ſaid the Wolf. So the Wolf preſently commanded the Army to ſtay and reſt themſelves there, where they were, but that the Commanders ſhould all repair unto him, now gone into the Court. Which order was ſcarcely well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, before the Wolf was entred within the Court-gate, he was in ſuch haſte to fill his belly, as he ſuppoſed he ſhould. Now with him Sir <hi>Tibert</hi> would have entred, but the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diligently watching, on purpoſe to prevent him, (for they had order ſo to do) put him by, ſaying, he might come in anon after the Nobles; adding alſo this, Here is not ſo much room within as to let in every one that comes. So <hi>Tibert</hi> waited till all the Lords were come to the Gate, &amp; ſeeing the guard of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to open themſelves to make way for them to come in, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed a Nephew of his to enter in at one ſide of the gate &amp; ſlip
<pb facs="tcp:64820:37"/> between the Soldiers Legs, and ſo get in. His Nephew old ſo, and was in. <hi>Tibert</hi> himſelf walked under <hi>Bruin's</hi> belly, and ſo was admitted uneſpied; after <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear all the other Commanders walked in, not one was miſſing, except <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, who was gone to his Couſin <hi>Reynard;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent for by him, or becauſe he ſuſpected the Treachery, is not known. When all were within, the Court-gates were ſhut; and all the Lords were immediately laid hold of, and ſecured; alſo <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat with them; but his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew ſeeing what was done, in great fear leapt over that Soldiers head, who would have taken him, and ſo eſcaped: Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> underſtanding that <hi>Tiberts</hi> Nephew was gone, knew it was high time to diſperſe the Army. Therefore he with four hundred Soldiers ſallyed out upon them, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them (who were before diſordered) in ſo furious a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as moſt of them fled, leaving their Arms behind them; many of were taken Priſoners, and ſent into the Court, but ſome few eſcaped and ran to <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox conſulting with his Uncle <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, returned to his Caſtle, and diſmiſſed part of his Soldiers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Fox greatly perplered at the ruin of his Army, of which he was too, tooſurely informed by the Run-aways, and having juſt before underſtood how all the Nobles were betrayed, he was almoſt at his wits end. <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Couſin <hi>Reynard</hi> ſo exceedingly overcome with grief, ſaid, Couſin, it is not the firſt time you have been in danger, and yet have overcome all difficulties, why not now? Ah, Uncle, ſaid the Fox, there is a vaſt difference between what I then was, and what I am now, or at leaſt was but three hours ago. And I too well know, that the greater any one is, when he falls his fall is ſo much the more dangerous. Before I vexed ſome few only, and thoſe not conſiderable
<pb facs="tcp:64820:37"/> perſons; but now I have diſpleaſed the King himſelf, and <note place="margin">Great diſaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſh the moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg thereof comes unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; as here is ſeen in the Fox, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, never had a ſhift to ſeek, yet now is ſo conſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as he knows not which way to turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> all his moſt intimate friends; therefore I muſt needs be utterly undone. But Couſin, ſaid the Ape, have you not made ſome proviſion before-hand to ſecure your ſelf in this time of need? For every one that is wiſe, will always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the worſt. Yes Uncle, I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve done as much as could be, for I fortified my Caſtle long before, and have ſtored it with all ſorts of Proviſion: but yet I am in a very great ſtrait: if I draw all this Company into <hi>Malepardu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> after me, their number is ſo great as I ſhall not be able to hold out a long Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, eſpecially if all the private Avenues of my Caſtle be ſtopped up, as they will be to be ſure, if the King with his Forces ſhall come to ſit down before it. For ſo ſoon as I, or my Soldiers ſhall be reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rained from forage, ſo many mouth &amp; will quickly devour all. And if I draw not in with me a ſufficient number to make ſallies out upon my Enemies, then they will adventure to ſtorm or blow up my Fort, and what ſhall become of us then? Truly, it is an hard caſe, Couſin, ſaid the Ape, but cheer up; and firſt of all, with-draw from this place, leaving the Kings high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake your ſelf and Soldiers to Covert, in ſome by Lane, that if the King purſue, he may not find you. Thus doing. you will have ſome reſpit to determine of your March. According to the Ape's advice, the Fox withdrew into a by Lane with all his Soldiers. Then his Uncle again ſaid to him, Now Couſin you need fear no ſurpriſal, at leaſt for an hour or two. If you like not to haſten to your Caſtle and there to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bide the brunt, what is your determination? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not at all judg it ſafe for us to go to the King, eſpecially whilſt his rage is at ſuch an height, as it muſt needs be at this time. Therefore I judg nothing will conduce more to our ſecurity, then to protract the time, the beſt way we can. Indeed Uncle, ſaid the For. I think it will be beſt to do as you ſay; but the many mouths we have to feed will endanger all. Why Couſin, you have a reme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y for that. Know you not that three or four hundred in a Fort, will be able to reſiſt ten thouſand in the Field. Yes Uncle; quoth the For, I well know it; yet I would have more than three hundred, yea
<pb facs="tcp:64820:38"/> more than four hundred Soldiers, if I were ſure not to be blockt up too ſuddenly. Couſin, Couſin, ſaid the Ape, you muſt determine ſomewhat ſpeedily: Be ruled by me, I pray chuſe out the weakeſt of your Soldiers and diſmiſs them, and retain none with you, but ſuch as are ſtout and reſolute Warriers. To this the Fox hearkned, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged thrée hundred and odd of the weakeſt, but the ſtrongeſt with him were near four hundred. his Army being increaſed by the Run-aways who were retained ſtill with him; and becauſe the night was far ſpent, and he durſt not abide where he was till day-light, he by a ſwift march came toh is own Caſtle by break of day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox was purſued, and many of his Soldiers that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, taken by the Purſuers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVHen <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, as is aforeſhewed, had routed and diſperſed the Army that lay before the Court; not long after it was thought convenient to ſend out other freſh Soldiers, in purſuit of the Fox and his Company. The Leader of theſe freſh Soldiers was one of the Kings Friends, that ſupped with him that night. He having no guide to direct him where to find the Fox, bade his Soldiers to lie in wait for ſtraglers. So they did, and in a ſhort time one of them laid hold of one of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> Lineage, and cried out a Spy, a Spy; the Captain hearing this, ſaid, bind him and bring him hither: When he was brought bound to the Captain, he asked him what he was? he told him, he was one of Sir <hi>Tiberts</hi> Kindred. Well then, ſaid the Captain, go along with us, and ſhew us the place where that Trayterous Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> is. So on they went with this their Guide to that very by-Lane in which <hi>Reynard</hi> and his Uncle <hi>Bitelas</hi> had béen, but were gone. Then he again examined the Guide, if he knew not where they were gone. The Guide told him, whither they
<pb facs="tcp:64820:38"/> were gone he could not tell, for whilſt they were with their Soldiers in that by-Lane, he was ſent out with ſeveral others to lie as near the Court, as they could, to give notice if any marched out to attaque the Lord <hi>Reynard.</hi> And that he having layn long thereabout, did at length return to that place, but found neither him, nor his Soldiers, except ſome few that were diſmiſſed by him, as they ſaid, and ſo were going to their own homes. Which way went they, ſaid the Captain? this way Sir, ſaid the Guide, (pointing weſtward from the Court) and if you haſten, you will overtake them, for they go not faſt. The Captain having this intelligence from the guide, commanded his Soldiers to follow cloſe. In a little time they found two or three, and paſſing further on, found ſeveral others by threes and fours in a Company; this courſe they held till they had gleaned up almoſt an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Then the Captain fearing to be over-burthened with too many Priſoners, gave command to purſue no further. So he with theſe Priſoners haſted to the King, but he had marched out ſo far in purſuit, as it was Sun-riſe ere he came to the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Examination of the Traytors and Priſoners.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen this Captain with his party were come into the Court, and the King by him underſtood that <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> was fled: He then, fearing no Enemy, commanded his Purveyors to bring Proviſion in abundance, that he and all his Friends might eat and be merry. The Purveyors mate ready as ſoon as was poſſible, and the King and all his Friends dined very chearfully; after this the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vitors dined. and what was left was given to the Captive Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but the Traytors all this while had neither eat nor drunk. Therefore the King commanded, that what the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners left, the Traytors ſhould have divided among them. This was done accordingly, and they had no more, any of
<pb facs="tcp:64820:39"/> them except <hi>Tibert,</hi> who by good fortune had a Mouſe given him by a certain Soldier, who found it dead and trod on in the Court. This preſent was ſo thankfully accepted by Sir <hi>Tibert,</hi> as he promiſed to requite him who gave it with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Booty, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ever he had his Liberty.</p>
               <p>When the King and his Friends had dined, as we ſaid; The King looking on Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly look,</hi> ſaid, Now my Noble Lords, I perceive you have told me a truth, you have in very deed convinced me of that which I could not otherwiſe have believed, although my incr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dulity had coſt me my life. I thank you both for your Loyalty, and all you my Friends for your faithful advice and aſſiſtance. Now I judg it convenient that we firſt examine the Priſoners, and afterward the Traytors; that if we find any not guilty, we may diſmiſs them. Then Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> ſtood up and ſaid Noble Prince, I do verily believe that all the Captive Priſoners are not guilty, for they were led by their Lords, but about what they could not tell, as by Examination your Majeſty will clearly find. Well then, ſaid the King, let <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Soldiers be firſt called. So when they were brought before the King, his Majeſty asked them, how they durſt take up arms againſt himſelf? Some of them anſwered, they were hired Soldiers, hired by the Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> and by him led forth the laſt night; but about what, or for what cauſe, they never knew, till ſome of the other Lord's Soldiers run in among them, ſaying, the whole Army was either killed, or taken; then indeed (ſaid they) we miſtruſted we were led againſt your Majeſty, but yet of that could not be aſſured, becauſe thoſe that fled from before the Court-gates unto us could not tell who were their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, only they ſaid, they who ſet upon them came all out at the Court-gates. The King hearing the ſimplicity of their anſwer diſmiſſed them, and all the other Priſoners, ſtrictly charging them to be ready at his Summons, when he thought good to hunt the Traytor <hi>Reynard.</hi> They all bowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves promiſed they would couragiouſly fight againſt the Kings Enemies. So they all departed ſafely to their own homes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:39"/>
               <p>This being done, the King ſaid, now my Friends, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that this is <hi>Reynard</hi>'s work, it is managed ſo craftily; for I plainly ſee, that not one of the Commons is guilty of this Treaſon, becauſe they knew not what they went about. Therefore let the Lord <hi>Pitwood</hi> be firſt called. So <hi>Pitwood</hi> was brought in before the King and his Friends, with <hi>Bellin</hi>'s Gown on his back, quaking and trembling: The King no ſooner ſaw him, but he ſternly ſaid, Pull off the Villain's diſguiſe, that we may ſee him, as he is. Then did Sir <hi>Firra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſsctors o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> baſe ſpirit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are in their aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected than others; and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ercour of puniſhment is moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s to ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>exation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eteſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aiſed evils; but from a ſenſe of being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to perſiſt in that courſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look,</hi> immediately tear off <hi>Bellin</hi>'s Gown, and when all the Company ſaw it was <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, they laughed heartily. As ſoon as they were all ſilent, the King ſaid. Thou wretch, what moved thee to conſpire my death, who from a low and vile eſtate advanced thee to ſo great Honour? Is Treaſon Religion? Or, is Murder and Treaſon virtue in a Prieſt? At theſe wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the Wolf was ſo frighted, as he piſt for fear. At length he ſaid, The Lord <hi>Reynard</hi> gave me preſents often, and often ſpake to me, that I ſhould commend him before the Lords, and at length perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them to eſtabliſh him in the Royal Throne. And was that all ſaid the King? Yes, all indeed Sir, ſaid the Wolf (and then piſt again) except that we muſt with hired Soldiers (who muſt know nothing before-hand of the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) come hither and kill your Majeſty and all the Royal Family, and then ſet the Crown on <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Head. Enough, enough, ſaid the King. Take away the Villain, and chain him to a ſtake, and ſo keep him, with bread and dirty water until I call for him. So the Keeper who had charge of this Priſoner, took him away, and bound, and fed him, according to the King's will.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox with his Soldiers made incurſions the next day ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly on ſeveral of the Neighbouring Beaſts, that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to the King.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>DVring</hi> the time the Fox was in proſperity, and had abundance of all things, either given by way of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, or obtained by Delinquents forfeitures, the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Beaſts, that dwelt not far from <hi>Reynards</hi> Caſtle, had reſt and peace, and therefore without fear were wont to walk abroad in the day-time all there about. But when <hi>Reynard</hi> was fled home in fear and great danger, with his Soldiers, intending there to abide a Siege, and protract the time as long as was poſſible, (for he knew he was now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of mercy) he on a ſudden ſet forth with two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Soldiers, who he commanded all to go ſilently along by the Hedges which encompaſſed a large Warren, where many Conies dwelt. Theſe Conies fearleſs, and ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Commonly, the moſt peaceable feel the firſt ſtrokes of War.</note> nothing, played and skipped about in the Sun-ſhine, as they were daily wont to do; but ſuddenly <hi>Reynard</hi> with his Soldiers ruſhed in among them, and flew two hundred outright preſently, all which he bore away to his Caſtle. And immediately returned again, where ſeveral She-goats fed their young ones, all which young ones he and his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſeized and carried home. Many other Incurſions he
<pb facs="tcp:64820:41"/> made that day further into the Country, and made great havock and ſpoil. At this all the Neighbouring Beaſts were alarum'd, and reſolved to ſtand upon their defence. But when they underſtood by the eldeſt of the Goats and Conies, who it was had done their Neighbours this great wrong, they reſolved joyntly to go together to the Court and complain to the King; for by this time they had all notice of <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Treaſon and Rebellion; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had no doubt but they ſhould be heard. So they in the Evening come in troops to the Court-gates, where the Guard ſeeing them, demand the cauſe of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thus in multitudes? They anſwer, We are come to complain to his Majeſty of the great Outrages <hi>Reynard</hi> and his company have committed. So the Guard ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the King, who immediately came forth to them; ſaying, Who is it that hath wronged you? The Conies anſwer, If your Majeſty be pleaſed to hear us, we will truly declare what we have ſuffred. The King ſaid, ſpeak, we will hear you. Then one of the eldeſt among them ſaid,</p>
               <p>Dread Soveraign, We your Majeſties peaceable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, being imployed about our occaſions in tending our young ones, drew them forth to take the Air in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Traytor <hi>Reynard</hi> lying in wait (as it ſeems) with many Soldiers, ſuddenly ſlew two hundred of us, (for ſo many young and old are miſſing) and bear away the Bodies to his Caſtle of <hi>Malepardus,</hi> for there we ſaw him plainly go in with all his Soldiers, every one of them bearing one of our dear Friends and Kinsfolks dead; this we could not have known, had not ſome of us adventured to run after them, to ſee which may they went, and who they were. Thus ſpake the Conies.</p>
               <p>The Goats alſo made a like complaint of ſudden ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing their Kid before they were aware. And all the other Beaſts who had ſuſtained wrong, exhibited their Complaints with tears in their eyes, earneſtly requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty to take compaſſioon of them, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
<pb facs="tcp:64820:41"/> their cauſe of ſuch a bloody Murtherer. The King (in a rage ſhaking his curled locks) ſaid, Be content, if I live I will avenge my ſelf and you, on that curſed Traytor <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> to morrow by this time, if poſſible. So they bowing themſelves very ſubmiſſively, departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King with his Kinsfolks, and the Soldiers of Sir <hi>Firrapel,</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look,</hi> marched out of the Court to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> and there ſummoned the Fox to ſurrender himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>EArly in the Morning the King willed Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look</hi> to command their Soldiers to make ready for a March, for he would ſpeedily march to <hi>Malepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> to be avenged of the Traytors <hi>Reynard</hi> and <hi>Bittelas.</hi> When the Soldiers were ready, the King ſets out firſt with his eldeſt Son, Kinsfolks and Friends; then followed Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin with their Soldiers, of whom, and of Servitors, one hundred were left in the Court, to keep Guard there, and ſecure the Priſoners. When all that were appointed for this Expedition were gone forth, the Court-gates were diligently ſhut; and the King himſelf being foremoſt, made an halt, and turning him to his Son, ſaid, Son, I this day commit the leading of the Army to your ſelf, that if poſſible you may have the honour of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out and ſubduing the crafty and Trayterous Varlet <hi>Rev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi> Therefore lead as you pleaſe, we all will follow, as well as we can. So this young Prince bowing himſelf to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Friends, ſaid no more, but ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rh on Sirs. And indéed he led ſo hard, without ſpeaking ought, as he got within fight of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pardus,</hi> before Noon. When he ſaw the place, he ſtood ſtill, and ſo did they all. Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he King ſaid, now Son it will be good to reſt here a while, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mean time to conſider w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t we have to do Firſt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> do our beſt to learn of what ſtrength our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be beſt to beſiege or aſſault th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if we do not one of theſe our labor will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will not come forth to fight us we muſt either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with our Soldiers, &amp; ſo by length of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, or ſuddenly
<pb facs="tcp:64820:42"/> with fire &amp; ſword endeavour to force the Caſtle, and ſo drive them forth. His Son ſaid, my Lord to ſend out Scouts to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what they can, is moſt neceſſary; but to begirt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, we have not Forces enough, neither is that conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent at preſent, becauſe we know not the private Avenues and Holes belonging to the Caſtle, how far they are exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">Here is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the danger of attempting any thing in War, without good advice. And how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Enemy's condition, is for a future management of Martial Affairs.</note> and ſo they may happen to lie within them, and by that means when we only expect an Enemy before us, they iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, aſſault us behind, and on every ſide ſuddenly. It is well thought on, ſaid the King. Therefore ſend out ſome of the nimbleſt Soldiers to eſpy whether they ſee any paſſing to &amp; from the Caſtle So Spies were ſent, and charged to lie cloſe at a good diſtance from the Caſtle round about. In a little time they diſcovered ſeveral Beaſts laden with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions to paſs in by holes under the Walls of <hi>Malepardus;</hi> and others not loaded, coming forth further off, and among thoſe Scouts there was one, who ſee the Earth caſt up juſt before him; he lying cloſe a little while, at length ſee <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> himſelf putting forth his Head; but he eſpying that the Coaſt was not clear, drew back: then did this Scout leap to the Hole, but the Fox had ſtiled it up ſo in that ſhort time, the Scout could not ſo much as put in one hand. He by this ſet a mark, and lay ſtill, at length he ſpyed one of <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Soldiers coming forth of another hole a little further off; him he ſuffred to come quite out, and then immediately ſeized him, and carryed him to the King. Others of the Scouts ſaw like paſſages, and ſome of them took of <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard's</hi> Soldiers three or four other that were laden and going to the Caſtle. When all the Scouts were returned, it was found by their Relation, that none went into the Caſtle laden by thoſe private holes, but by larger holes juſt under the Caſtle-walls. The King hearing this, examined the four Priſoners that were taken laden with Proviſious fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt; they tell him, that the Fox and his Uncle <hi>Bitelas</hi> were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Caſtle, and that with them the Soldiers in number were not above Three hundred ſeventy-five in all, and that he had ſtore of Proviſions of all ſorts; yet fearing that
<pb facs="tcp:64820:42"/> would not be enough, one half of the Soldiers were yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day imployed in foraging, and the other half to day; withal adding, if his Majeſty were pleaſed be might take near an hundred of them with their booty in a ſhort time, for near ſo many were ſtill out, and had not returned ſince morning; becauſe they who went out yeſterday had ſo alarum'd the Country thereabouts, as near home nothing could be got. Then the King immediately ſent out a great Party, here and there to lie in wait on every ſide. Having done this, he examined the Soldier that was taken coming out of an hole that lead from the Caſtle. He ſaid, that the Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> (as he ſtill called him) being informed by the Soldiers, who returned into the Caſtle with their Booty, that there were lyers in wait, and that your Majeſty was near with an Army, was reſolved to go forth by that Avenue where he was ſeen to put out his head, to ſee whether the report was true, and finding by his own experience that it was too true, he preſently commanded me to run to the Soldiers that are yet out, and bid them to retire into Covert till night, and then come home; this I had done, had I not been taken, as your Majeſty ſees. So the King gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to ſecure the Priſoners, yet that they ſhould be uſed well. After this, the King again conſulting with his Lords, determined to ſend a Summons to <hi>Reynard</hi> to deliver him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Caſtle into the Kings hand. This Summons they judged convenient to ſend ſpeedily, before the Fox knew what ſtrength the King had, leaſt in the night he ſhould work them ſome miſchief. So Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, <note place="margin">Traytors ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forſeited their Lives grow deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and will hearken to no Summons, but at the hearing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are the more enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> with what Company he pleaſed, was appointed to Summon the Fox to deliver up his Caſtle. Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> accordingly took forty Soldiers with him, and came as near to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as he thought he might with ſafety, and called aloud, Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> Sir <hi>Reynard,</hi> his Majeſty commands you to deliver up your Fort, with all the Ammunition you have, into his hands this night, otherwiſe he is reſolved to uſe all extremity to force it. By that time he had ended his Speech, a ſhower of ſtones was poured down upon him and
<pb facs="tcp:64820:43"/> his Soldiers, which hurt many of them, and doubtleſs had they been nearer, would have killed moſt of them. Sir <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapel</hi> thus anſwered, haſtens to the King, and ſhews him ſome of his Soldiers wounded. Vpon this the King reſolves to be revenged; therefore ſaid to his Son, Son, I ſee it will be long work, and we have not ſoldiers enough to lay a cloſe Siege. Therefore when thoſe you have ſent out be come in, encamp your ſelves as ſecurely as you can, either in the place where you are, or further off from the Caſtle, not failing to keep good Guard all night; and I in the mean time will return home, and ſend out my Mandates for raiſing the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſpeedily, and then undoubtedly we ſhall diſpatch this buſineſs to our content. So the King went to Court, and his Son encamped the Army, who for that night ſupped with what the Scouts brought in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox's Soldiers in the night aſſailed the King's Camp, and what enſued thereupon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter Supper the Watch was ordered, and Officers appointed to change the Centries often, alſo to ſet Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues to lie round about the Camp. All this while the Fox was not idle, but being extreamly diſcontented that he had loſt ſo many of his Soldiers (for the King's Scouts brought in above forty with their Booties) ſtudied how he might moſt annoy his Enemies in the Night. Therefore in the deed of the Night he ſent out a party of three hundred, adviſing them to march ſilently, and to encompaſs the Camp round, and when they were drawn very near to it in their encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing, all at once to cry out aloud, Now for the Lord <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard;</hi> and then immediately to aſſault the Centries firſt, and afterward the Camp it ſelf (for he knew the Enemy were encamped very cloſe together, ſo as three hundred Soldiers all in a File might conveniently encompaſs it) on every ſide. This party was led by his Uncle <hi>Bitelas</hi> (for the Fox would rather loſe all the Friends he had, than endanger his own
<pb facs="tcp:64820:43"/> perſon) who very ſlyly marched his Soldiers in the form of an half Moon, that ſo they might keep together, and yet be in a poſture ready to begirt the Camp ſuddenly. This enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of his was perceived by the Purdues, and timely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence given to the Lord <hi>Firrapel,</hi> who himſelf watched. He therefore on the other ſide of the Camp drew out his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, <note place="margin">This Chapter ſhews how provident Commander<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> enervate and fruſtrate the policy and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> their Enemies.</note> which he had in readineſs, and dividing them in two parts, led one part himſelf, and left the other part to the leading of his Lieutenant; then march they ſoftly round the Camp of two ſides to meet with the Horns of the Enemies Half-Moon, which they quickly met with, engaged and routed, and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſued them till they were driven cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, juſt before the other Gate of the Camp, right oppoſite to that out of which the Lord <hi>Firrapel</hi> Iſſued; the other Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that were at reſt in the Camp, being allarum'd, they flank their Enemies, who were turned both ways to reſiſt the Lord <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Lieute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>; in this miſerable plight, ſome throw down their Arms and yield themſelves Priſoners, others are ſlain outright, (among which <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, their Captain, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one) many taken, becauſe of their Wounds, which prevented their flight and ſome eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pd to carry the News to <hi>Malepardus.</hi> After the fight was done, they numbred the Captives, and found them to be a hundred and ſix, the dead they accounted not till morning; but then it appeared, that of the King's Soldiers were ſlain ſix, and ſeveral wounded; but of <hi>Reynards</hi> Forces forty eight, ſo that of the three hundred that iſſued out of <hi>Malepardus,</hi> there returned but a hundred and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſix. Thus in one day and a night <hi>Reynard</hi> loſt two hundred of his three hundred ſeventy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five Soldiers, which he ſeared would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e too many.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King gave command to proclaim all Traytors that aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Reynard,</hi> promiſing pardon to thoſe that would deſert him, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>EArly in the morning the news of this Victory, and of death of <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, was carryed to Court by one purpoſely ſent thither to acquaint his Majeſty how mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters went. The King greatly pleaſed with the newes, thought of another way to weaken <hi>Reynard,</hi> before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey did come in. Therefore he by the ſame Meſſenger ſent an expreſs order to his Son to draw out all his Forces out of the Camp, and to march to <hi>Malepardus,</hi> as cloſe as was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and there in his name to proclaim all Traytors, that aſſiſted <hi>Reynard,</hi> withal promiſing pardon to all that would deſert him. Vpon this Meſſage the King's Son drew out all the Forces he had (leaving not one in the Camp, for he feared no enemy) and marched dirctly to <hi>Malepardus;</hi> being thither come, and within the hearing of thoſe within, he commanded ſilence, and afterward cauſed the Cryer to proclaim all Traytors that aſſiſted <hi>Reynard,</hi> but preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to all thoſe who would within three hours deſert him. <note place="margin">It is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen, that the followers of Traytors, readily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, when they ſee a probability of ſecuring themſelves.</note> Vpon the hearing of this, near an hundred of <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Soldiers fled from him, and came and offred their Service to the King. But ere this was effected, ſome thouſands of the Commons who had been ſummoned by the King, marched toward <hi>Malepardus.</hi> The King's Son ſeeing them, ſent out certain Scouts to enquire what they were? they anſwer, they were ſummoned by the King to come and aſſiſt his Son, in taking the Traytor <hi>Reynard.</hi> So the young Prince being glad of this Supply, did forthwith command them to begirt the Caſtle. They accordingly lie down before it all that day, but ſée no enemy appear. In the mean while, the King's Son orders the Lord <hi>Firrapel,</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Sly-look,</hi> to imploy their Soldiers to march at ſome diſtance round about <hi>Malepardus,</hi> that whereſoever they ſaw any Avenues,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:44"/>
                  <figure/> or private holes, they might ſtop them with heavy ſtones; withal commanding to ſet out Scouts, who ſhould lie cloſe in manner of Purdues, the better to deſcry the outgoing of the Enemies. All theſe things being done, no Enemy was ſeen, either to appear in the Caſtle, or to come forth by thoſe private Avenues, (which as faſt as they could they
<pb facs="tcp:64820:45"/> ſtopped) or by any other new made hole. Therefore now nothing was thought on but a ſtorm, yet night being ſo near, they judged it not ſeaſonable to begin the Aſſault un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til morning; in the mean while, care was taken that the Holes and Avennes ſhould be watched all night. This was accordingly done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox's Caſtle was ſtorme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and all within it killed, onely <hi>Reynard</hi> himſelf taken alive, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>Early on the Morrow ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>being brought, and all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Soldiers only waited for the word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard <note place="margin">Bold Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardons, therefore the wiles of an Enemy ſhould always be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected.</note> was commanded with its Soldiers to begin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault. But the Fox who all this while was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> provided for their coming before-hand, and round about the Caſtle-Walls on the inſide had digged deep Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of a great depth, which ſtood fall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter, by him drawn thither from a Spring, which ſtood within his Caſtle. Over this Trench upon the Walls he had made a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſe Batilement ſeemingly ſtrong, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> when four hundred of the Soldiers (commanded by Sir F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pel) had go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up, the Battlements breaking down, they fall into the Trenches, where mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them drowned one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in ſtriving to get out, the reſidue were killed by <hi>Reynards</hi> Soldiers.</p>
               <p>This overthrow perplexed <hi>Sir Firrapel</hi> and the Prince exceedingly; for the poſſibility of ſtorming it. ſeemed now to be taken away. Therefore the Prince conſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with all his Friends abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the preſent Buſineſs. After a little time it was agreed by went to ſord up certain Soldiers to the top of the Wall, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not to attempt to leap down, <hi>what</hi> provocation ſoever was given, but to ſhoot and ſling at their Enemies, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were, and to eſpy <hi>how the</hi> Avenues belonging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Caſtle had their
<pb facs="tcp:64820:45"/> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let. They accordingly march up round about the Caſtle, <note place="margin">Here is ſeen h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Aſſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants dv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring toor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, are taught by their own loſs to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward more wary.</note> and met with no ſmall provocations from the Enemy (who were but few in number) yet they obſerved what they were commanded, and between whiles well viewed the Trench and over if they eſpyed ſeveral Bridges, many in number round about, yet all of them were ſo narrow, as but one Soldier could paſs a-breaſt upon them at once. This intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence being given to the Prince, he commanded two thouſand Soldiers to imploy themſelves in opening the Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, and making them wider, which was ſpeedily done; then he ordered more Soldiers to aſcend the Walls, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to amuſe the Enemy, giving them command to ſhout and ſling, but keeping in their places. Whilſt this was doing he ſent in ſix hundred Soldiers through the Avenues, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to fight reſolutely, and get over the Bridges, then to ſlay all they found in the Caſtle, except only <hi>Reynard</hi> himſelf; and for their encouragement he promiſed them among them full one half of the Booty that ſhould be taken <note place="margin">Promiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> neceſſary in dangerous attempts.</note> therein; and that if any died in the Attempt (as he hoped none would) his Wife and Children ſhould have all his part duly given to them.</p>
               <p>With this encouragement they boldly entred the Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, ſome of which ſtunk ſo abominably, as the Soldiers were almoſt poyſoned; nevertheleſs they haſtned forward, and got to the mouths of thoſe Holes where they plainly ſaw the Bridges, and <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Soldiers ſtanding here and there one, very near them. But by the mouths of the Holes they ſaw another out-let, one of which being opened, it was found to be one of them Holes, by which the For's Soldiers were wont to enter, when laden with Booty. Vpon this Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> gave command, that all the other Holes (whcih were as many as there were private Avenues ſhould be opened; this was accordingly done by the ſix hundred Soldiers, who were in thoſe Avenues, but du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt not beware over the Bridges. Now when they ſaw great m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bers might ſpeedily have entrance that way to back them, they were encouraged and boldly
<pb facs="tcp:64820:46"/> ſet forward. Yet in the mean while <hi>Reynard</hi>'s Soldiers attempted to pluck up the Bridges; but becauſe they were ſhot at, both from the top of the Walls, and alſo from the mouths of the Holes, they could not effect what they deſired. Therefore as they gave back, the Kings Soldiers came for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and in a very ſhort time above one thouſand got over the Bridges; then they flew about like wild Beaſts, kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all they ſound, and indeed all that were in the Caſtle died at that time; and <hi>Reynard</hi> himſelf was knockt down with a Battle-are by a Soldier who knew him not; but his fellow ſeeing him about to kill the Fox, ſaid, That is the Traytor himſelf. Then that Soldier who had knockt him down, led him out of the Caſtle, and carryed him to the Prince, who rejoiced excéedingly that his Enemy was taken alive. After this, the Soldiers that firſt entred, had half the Booty, and the reſidue was divided among the whole Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of diſſolving of the Army, and how <hi>Reynard</hi> the Fox was carryed Priſoner to the Court, and what paſſed after this.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AS ſoon as this work was ended, and the Caſtle demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the Prince ſent home all thoſe Soldiers who were raiſed by Summons for his Aſſiſtance immediately, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the two hundred Soldiers of Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rained alive, and all his other Friends, he marched to Court leading the Fox along with them. A little before Sun-ſet they were all come to the Court, where they were welcomed by the King, with great expreſſions of Ioy, only ſome ſorrow was intermixed by reaſon of the loſs of thoſe four hundred brave Soldiers who were drowned and killed by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> policy. Therefore the King at that time before he ſat down, declared that the two hundred Soldiers yet living ſhould be retained as a Guard for his Perſon, and over them Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard ſhould be chief comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and his Lieutenant-General of all Forces that ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:64820:46"/> be raiſed at any time ever after, when need ſhould be. But unto <hi>Sly-look</hi> the Panther, <hi>Firrapel</hi>'s Couſin, he ſaid, As for you my Lord I intend to conſtitute you the Keeper of my Stores, and Steward of my Houſe. After this, he ſpake to all his Friends, praiſing their readineſs and valour; and to them he promiſed Gifts and Rewards, as ſoon as all his trouble was over; therefore he willed and deſired them not to depart, until the Execution of <hi>Reynard</hi> and all the Traytors was paſſed.</p>
               <p>When the King had ended his Speech, his Son asked him, if he would ſee the Traytor <hi>Reynard?</hi> The King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No, not at this time, let him be bound, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently lookt too, that he eſcape not; Vpon this, the Soldiers that guarded the Fox, haled him to the Priſon, and there in a ſtinking hole chained him to a ſtake, that was fixed in the ground.</p>
               <p>Then the King royally feaſted his Friends, and the two Lords, <hi>Firrapel</hi> and <hi>Sly-look.</hi> Alſo to every Company of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers he ſent a large Pittance, ſo they all feaſted right joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: But the Priſoners in the hearing of all this were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt pined with hunger, eſpecially <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf. After the Feaſt was over, and all the Kings Servitors had ſupped, they gave to every Priſoner a few ſcraps, and carryed into them a ſmall quantity of dirty water. And indeed their uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was ſo hard, as they all even wiſhed Death rather than Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Fox was brought before the King. and Examined; of the Anſwer he gave; and how he and all the other Traytors were condemned.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON the Morrow the King ſitting among his Nobles and Friends, ſaid, I ſuppoſe it is now high time that we call <hi>Reynard</hi> before us. To which they all aſſented. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>Firrapel</hi> went to the Priſon, and commanded that <hi>Reynard</hi> ſhould be brought forth. His Keeper preſently obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, looſed <hi>Reynard</hi> from the Stake to which he was chained, and by his Chain led him into the Kings Preſence. The King at the ſight of him was ſo fraught with Ire as he could not ſpeak, until a little time being paſſed, his fury was allayed; then he ſaid aloud, Falſe Miſcreant, how dareſt thou to hold up thy head, (for the Fox ſeemingly undaunted, ſtedfaſtly looked upon the King) who art ſo loaden with Vices, as the worſt of all living Creatures is not more <note place="margin">Politick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble their fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r till an aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their them relent.</note> vile! Was it not enough for you (baſe Traytor) to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into my affections ſo far, by Diſſimulations (as now I have great reaſon to judg) as to engage me to inveſt that monſtrouſly wicked and cruel Beaſt <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> with an Office (due to the beſt of Creatures) and Title ſo honourable; but alſo to perſwade me to create perfidious <hi>Bruin</hi> Earl of the Foreſts; and laſt of all (as if before you had not been vile enough) to inſtigate theſe and all my Nobles at once againſt me; and all this for your own baſe ends, which can never be accompliſhed? Have I honoured you for this end? Or would any Creature living have thought, that he who I moſt honoured, would have conſpired my Ruin moſt? What ſayeſt thou to this?</p>
               <p>To this, the Fox ſaid not one word; but at laſt hung down his head. The King ſaid, ſpeak wretch, or I will pronounce Sentence againſt you ſpeedily. At laſt the Fox ſaid, My Lord, I have ſo many Enemies that it will be in vain to ſay any thing contrary to what they have affirmed;
<pb facs="tcp:64820:47"/> and ſince I know I muſt die; I here before your Majeſty declare I am guilty of what is laid to my charge, and would have ſlain your Majeſty (for which I am now right ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) if my deſign had not been fruſtrated by the Treaſon of <hi>Firrapel</hi> and his Couſin. It is enough, ſaid the King, call in all the other Traytors, that as they all conſpired toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo they may together hear their Sentence of Death juſtly to be pronounced againſt them; and then their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſhall quickly follow. So all the Traytors were brought in. Then did the King with the advice of his Friends, in this manner proceed to Iudgment. Since you are now all together (except <hi>Bitelas</hi> the Ape, who died a death too honourable for his Merit) we judg it meet, you ſhould all hear your Sentence at one time. Therefore <hi>Reynard</hi> firſt hearken to your Sentence: Becauſe you have Trayterouſly endeavoured the Subverſion of our Government, and Royal Dignity, I condemn you to Death, in this manner to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon you. Firſt, you ſhall be dragged contumelouſly from this Place to the Place of Execution, and there your right hand ſhall be cut off, afterward you ſhall be hanged by the neck until you are dead, dead. After death your Head ſhall be cut off, and together with your right hand be ſet up in publick view, on ſome conſpicuous place, for a terror to all Traytors for the future. Vnto the Wolf he alſo repeated the above-ſaid words, and pronounced the ſame Sentence exactly in all points. But on all the other Traytors, he only pronounced the Sentence of Death in manner and form as you have heard, except in cutting off their heads, and right hands, which was not mentioned in their Sentences.</p>
               <p>After this the Priſoners were taken away until the place and time of Execution was fully determined, and agreed on by the King and his Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Fox's Conſeſſion, and the Execution of himſelf and all the Traytors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the Evening of the ſame day that Iudgment was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the King and his Friends again conſulted together, about the place and time of Execution. At length it was agreed on, that the place ſhould be on the outſide of that Foreſt, out of which the Traytors marched to put their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in execution. And the time, the next morning early. In the mean while, that all things ſhould be provided in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Priſoners have notice of their death ſo near approaching.</p>
               <p>Now when the Morrow was come, and the King and his Friends were gone before to take their ſtandings commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to avoid the Preſs; (which they knew would be great) The Fox himſelf, and all the other Traytors were led out of their ſeveral Priſons; then were their legs and hands tyed, the Halters with which they were to be hanged, were faſtned about their necks, and by them they were dragged (with houtings and ſhouts of the multitude) to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: When there, Ladders were erected againſt the Trees, (which were more than enough to hang all the Traytors) and each Priſoner, by his Executioner, led up thoſe Ladders, and immediately the Executioners faſtned the ropes to the Trees (ſuppoſing they muſt be hanged as ſoon as they came there) becauſe it was the cuſtom of their Country in other Caſes to hang Malefactors preſently; but the King ſpake to the Executioners, and ſaid, Be not too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſty, if any of the Priſoners will purge himſelf by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he ſhall have as free liberty as any one of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects hath, who dieth on his bed. The Fox hearing this, ſaid:</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>the execution of Reynard the Fox</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The King having ſaid this, ordered the Executioner to do his Office; ſo he immediately cut off <hi>Reynard's</hi> right hand, and afterward turned him off the Ladder. In the mean while the King ſpake to Sir <hi>Iſegrim</hi> the Wolf, and ſaid, <hi>Iſegrim</hi> have you any thing to ſay before the Executioner do his Office? Nothing Sir, ſaid the Wolf, (looking roguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) except that I was drawn in by the Fox's ſubtilty, and his great promiſes made me forget my Loyalty to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and readily to abſolve both him and Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> of their oath of fidelity ſworn to your Majeſty, and by me admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred. Oh execrable Villain, ſaid the King, what! durſt you releaſe any Subject of his ſworn fealty to us? After this the King would not hear him any further; but ſpake to the Executioner, and ſaid, Diſpatch this Varlet out of my fight
<pb facs="tcp:64820:49"/> quickly. So the Executioner preſently cut off his hand, and then turned him off the Ladder. Next to him Sir <hi>Bruin</hi> the Bear was asked, if he had ought to ſay? but he anſwered, No; and ſo was quickly turned off. After him all the reſt in order were asked, if they would ſay any thing before they died? but they all anſwered, They could ſay no more than they had already ſaid in their Examination; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were all turned off. After it was ſuppoſed the Traytors were dead the King gave command they ſhould be cut down, and their bodies buried in one Pit. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they were all cut down, being all ſtark dead, except <hi>Tibert</hi> the Cat, who ſtirred a little, therefore his brains were beat out by one of the Guard, and the bodies of them all were thrown into one Pit, except the Heads and right Hands of <hi>Reynard</hi> and <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> which were carryed to the Palace, and there ſet on Poles, placed on the uppermoſt Tower of the ſame, ſo high as they might be eaſily ſeen by all that paſſed by the Court.</p>
               <p>Thus have you as true an account of theſe matters as ever was given by any man that ſaw them not. If you would know what this grand Treaſon produced, peruſe the following Chapters which will inform you more plainly than can be expreſſed without a Fable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King and all his Nobles returning home, ruminated the Fox's Confeſſion, and what was the effect of their conſultation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVHen the Traytors were buried, and the Hands and Heads of <hi>Reynard</hi> and <hi>Iſegrim</hi> fixed upon Poles, as is ſaid. The King and his Nobles (being come home) ſat down together in the Court, all of them pondering much the words of <hi>Reynard</hi> touching <hi>Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins</hi> death. At length the King (as one greatly perplexed ſaid, My Lords, &amp; Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds, it grieves me not a little, that our Chapl. <hi>Bellin,</hi> was long ſince ſo baſely put to death and his Family ruined ſo, as I queſtion whether
<pb facs="tcp:64820:50"/> any of that Stock be now remaining in the World. To <note place="margin">Although in nocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may long remain injured, yet in proceſs of time, the cauſe of their oppreſſion comes to be known and then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is nigh at hand.</note> this, one of the Kings Friends (who was preſent when <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was choſe chief Prelate) ſaid, Soveraign Lord, think not ſo, for I am certain, that many of them were living when <hi>Iſegrim</hi> was made Prelate; becauſe I there ſaw ſeveral of them, but would not be known I ſaw them, for fear of your Majeſties diſpleaſure againſt them. Sure ſaid the King it is not poſſible! I ſuppoſe your eye deceived you; however, if it were ſo then, it is too probable, that they are all dead ſince, becauſe the Sons and KIndred of <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> although very numerous, had all of them Furr-Gowns like <hi>Bellin's</hi> (which <hi>Iſegrim</hi> himſelf wore) not long after they were confirmed in the Prieſtly Function: for many more of <hi>Iſegrim's</hi> Kindred came into him after the choice of the Commons, than were that day preſent upon the Scaffold with us, and yet all theſe had ſuch Fur-Gowns, which they could never have had, if ſo many of <hi>Bellin's</hi> Kindred had not been firſt ſlain and ſtript, &amp;c. To this, the ſame Lord replied, Noble Sir, I am moſt certain, that in ſecret places of your Majeſties Realm, there are thouſands of them yet living. It is well if it be ſo, ſaid the King. After this Diſcourſe was ended, the King again ſaid. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Friends, I too well know, that we have confirmed the Prieſtly Office, not on <hi>Iſegrim</hi> only, but on his whole Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Kindred, who are all revenous Beaſts void of all goodneſs; nay I think, the worſt of all Creatures living; although the Fox by his ſubtilty blinded my eyes, and <hi>Iſegrims</hi> pretended demure carriage alienated my Iudgment. For had honeſt <hi>Bellin</hi> yet lived, treacherous <hi>Reynard</hi> could never have thought of working our ruin; nor ever could that curſed Miſcreant <hi>Iſegrim,</hi> have contributed any aſſiſtance to his diſloyal intentions. The young Prince ſeeing his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeak with ſo great earneſtneſs, ſaid, Royal Father, why is your Majeſty troubled at the Advancement of <hi>Iſegrims</hi> Lineage, let it be ſignified by Proclamation, that in their Father's Crime, they have all forfeited their Offices; and beſides, that upon good and ſure grounds, your Majeſty well
<pb facs="tcp:64820:50"/> knows, that they are the Deſtroyers of your Subjects, and continually in their masked Habits, and under a pretence of Sanctity they rob, and pill them ſo bare, as of neceſſity your Kingdom muſt be ruined if they be permitted to live in all exceſs and riot; for of all the Beaſts under your Majeſties Authority, there are none ſo debauched and vicious as they. This Spéech of the Prince was ſeconded by ſeveral others of the Kings Friends, all inveighing bitterly againſt <hi>Iſegrim's</hi> Lineage. The King hearing this, ſaid, Sirs, what think you is beſt to be done? If we lay aſide this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration (I mean diſplace them of their Offices) and yet let them hold their Wealth, they may in time by their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches work us great wrong. To this that Friend of the Kings <note place="margin">Prudent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to avoid Vulgar cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> who firſt ſpake, ſaid, Noble Sir, to lay aſide this impious ſtock is honourable; but to take away their Wealth will have no good aſpect in the eyes of the Vulgar (whoſe cenſure is ſeldom right) becauſe they will impute their diſplacing to ariſe from no other cauſe, then that they were rich, or (to ſpeak more plainly) becauſe your Majeſty was diſpoſed to <note place="margin">Many men willingly are blinded, and by cunning Sycophants opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſed: becauſe they jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of things a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a: and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> ſeize on all they had. Therefore if your Majeſty pleaſe to diſplace the Wolves, there needs no care to be taken of the Wealth they have; for if other of your Subjects, whoſe eyes are open, do but once find that they are out of your Majeſty's favour, which way the wealth of theſe Miſcreants muſt néeds go, any one (without the help of Aſtrology) may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture; becauſe whenſoever they are diſplaced and out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, there will be ſo many Complaints made of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions, as (undoubtedly) all they have will be too little to make recompence for the wrong they have done. Beſides if none of all this be, they are ſuch monſtrous Gluttons as will be neceſſitated to eat up all in a ſhort time. You ſay well, ſaid the King; I heartily believe, if all thoſe Wolves were but ſtript of this their diſguiſe, and compelled to put off their Furr-Gowns; the Blind then would as clearly ſee as the <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks and Diſguiſes conſtrain m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt men to judg ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> other clear ſighted Beaſts you ſpeak of. It is true, noble King, (ſaid the ſame Lord) pull but off the Mask, there need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no more. Well then ſaid the King, that I will not fail to do ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King made Proclamation, that no Beaſts ſhould walk diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed in other Garments, than what were naturally theirs, and what enſued thereupon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe</hi> next day early the King cauſed a Proclamation to be drawn, the tenour whereof ran thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo Rex,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas ſeveral of our Subjects wear Diſguiſes, and ſince under ſuch Masks and falſe Habits, many Miſchiefs have been committed, and ſome of thoſe Perſons allowed to wear ſuch like Diſguiſes, have proved Traytors to our Royal Crown and Dignity; We therefore will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all our Subjects in general, whether high or low, of what ſtate or condition ſo ever, that after ten days next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the Publication hereof, they preſume not to wear any Diſguiſe whatſoever, nor at any time, day or night, to walk clothed in other Garments, than what are naturally their own; upon pain of being proceeded againſt as Traytors to our Royal Crown and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Having ſaid this, he diſmiſſed the Lords, who were ſat in Counſel with him. So the Wolves departed ſad enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King deſirous to ſee ſome of <hi>Bellins</hi> Kindred, cauſed three of the oldeſt of them to be ſent for, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>AFter</hi> the Wealth of the Wolves was thus taken, and the Kings jealouſie thereabout allayed, he became very pleaſant and merry; and in that merry mood, ſaid, My <note place="margin">When the cauſe of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, cheerfulneſs neceſſarily follows.</note> Friends, I ſhould be glad to ſee ſome of the Rams Kindred; therefore if any of you know them our pleaſure is, that he go to them, and bring two or three of the oldeſt among them, before us. Then the Lord, who had before told the King there were thouſands of them living in ſecret places, ſaid, If it be your Majeſties pleaſure to ſee any of <hi>Bellins</hi> ſtock, I can eaſily ſatisfie your Majeſty therein, for I am fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly acquainted with many of them, eſpecially with <hi>Bellins</hi> Grandſon, and two more of the Eldeſt of them, who by reaſon of their diſcretion, have retired themſelves from the fury of the Bear and Wolf, and live ſafely in a ſmall piece of ground well fenced. The King hearing this, ſaid, Send for the three you ſpeak of, or go your ſelf and fetch them. So that Lord immediately went to the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, where they three dwelt alone; and firſt ſaluted them (as he was wont at other times) afterward told his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, withal in what condition the Wolfs Kindred ſtood, and how they were like to loſe their Offices ſuddenly. They knowing the realty of their Friend doubted nothing, but went along with him to the Court. When they were thither come, they by the ſame Lord, were brought into the Kings preſence, who looking cheerfully upon them, ſaid, I am glad to ſee you indeed, for I ſuppoſed you had been all deſtroyed before this time. I do confeſs, when I gave my conſent to the publiſhing that Edict, I thought I had done that which was right; but ſince underſtanding by the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Reynards</hi> own words, that he was the Murtherer of <hi>Kay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and not your Father; I heartily repented of what I
<pb facs="tcp:64820:53"/> had done. Therefore before you depart from us, we will <note place="margin">And a good P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſented to the wrong of other, through the perfidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> actings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eacheroo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perſons is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fied till he hath compleatly recompenced that wrong as tar as is poſſible.</note> aholiſh that law, and every part of it totally, as if it had never béen. Accordingly that Law was repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id that very day, and Proclamation made, that if any B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt whatſoever committed any out-rage againſt any of <hi>Bellins</hi> Lineage, young or old, they thould die for it. Vpon this, theſe three perſons were ſo well ſatisfied and aſſured of their peace and ſafety, as they came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſit this Lord, and ſometimes went in to the King himſelf, owning his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and protection as the greateſt happineſs that could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them. Alſo the King himſelf delighted in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany very much; for ſéeing their ſimplicity, and good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, he was not weary of ſeeing them, but rather thought they were long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſent, if he ſaw them not once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the Wolves behaved themſelves in their Offices after the Date of the Proclamation was expired, and how they were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ruined.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>By</hi> this time the ten days expreſſed in the Kings Precle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation were fully ended, and the Wolves (much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wills) had laid a ſide their Diſguiſes. Vpon this whenſoever any one of the Commons came to any of their Houſes to commune with them, or preſent them any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; ſo ſoon as he ſaw the Wolf (not masked) he would run away as hard as he could; and acquaint all he met, that he went to one of the Prelates Sons, and ſound none in his houſe, except a Wolf lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king gaſtly upon him. The Wolv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving they were utterly undone, if their Cilen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſhould be couſtantly thus frighted, knew not what courſe to take: therefore the ſubtileſt of them, when any of the Commons came, either to ſee them, or to pay their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, or to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them with ought, laid themſelves down, pretending they were not well; and that they might not be ſeen as they were, they ſpread over them a Coverlet of ſome other skin,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:54"/> (as if they were laid in a Sweat by the Phiſicians order) and ſo under that would ſpeak adviſing them to leave what they brought, in ſuch or ſuch a corner of the Houſe. This ſhift held water a while, but long it could not; for the moſt inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and the youngeſt of the Wolves would rather run the hizard than be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ved; therefore they again put on their Gowns, and ſuch as came to them then, were not frighted, as the other (who ſaw them without thoſe Gowns) had been. But ſo ſoon as this was bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zed abroad, ſome of <hi>Bellins</hi> friends <note place="margin">Wolfiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures when openly ſeen, are abomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to all.</note> came to the Houſes of theſe fooliſh Wolves, and well mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them, ſaid nothing, but went and immediately infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt them; offering to prove their contempt of the King and his Lawe. When this their Relation was heard by the King, he ſent for thoſe Wolves, and after proof made of their contempt, he hanged up Seventéen of them; for no more were then taken the other being fled for fear. The Execution of theſe terrifled all the other ſo, as if you would have perſwaded them (with an aſſurance of never ſo great ſeer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) to have put their Gowns on again but for one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, they would not have done it; nay, they abſolutely hated that G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b ever after. By this means the Wolves were in extre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m penury; and needs muſt ſo be; for in a very ſhort time it was known to all the Commons, that the Liueage of <hi>Pitwood,</hi> and be himſelf, had been and were, all very Wolves, and that Furr, Gown which <hi>Pitwood</hi> himſelf wore, and all the Gowns of his Lineage, were the true and natural Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Bellin,</hi> and <hi>Bellins</hi> Kindred, which Garments they took from them, as often as any one of that Race fell into their hands. The matter being thus clearly known, the King had no need to think of diſplacing them; becauſe their Office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fell from them immediately after it was fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. For all the Commons did not only fly from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rm, but alſo hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d together againſt them; &amp; if in the day-time any one of them ſtirred abroad, he was in danger of his Life, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, A Wolf, a Wolf, kill him, kill him. This hard uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge made the Wolves to keep cloſe,
<pb facs="tcp:64820:54"/>
                  <figure/> and not be ſeen abroad at all in the day-time; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they of neceſſity muſt go forth to purvey for food, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they did, but always in fear of being taken; ſo as they ever after led a poor and miſerable Life, until they e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died, or were forgot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:64820:55"/>
               <head>CHAP XXXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How the King rejoycing at the Wolves ruin, diſtributed their wealth among the Commons, and then openly ſhewed his love to <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lin's</hi> Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dred, and commanded all his Subjects to fellow their-Inſtructions, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen</hi> the King ſaw the effect of his Proclamation, what a ruin it had brought on <hi>Iſegrims</hi> Lineage, he was highly contented in his mind, and ſaid, (to that Lord, who before ſaid, Pull but off the Mask, and there needs no more) now my Friend the Mask is off, and there needs no more. With that, the ſame Lord bowed himſelf, and ſaid, Your Majeſty is now freed from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are of diſplating them. But who would have thought, they ſhould ſo ſuddenly have been ruined? How could it be otherwiſe, ſaid the King? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Traytor <hi>Reynard</hi> well knew, that <hi>Iſegrim</hi> would never have been admitted by the Commons into his Office, had he not worn that Diſguiſe. For <hi>Iſegrim</hi> and his whole Tribe were always hateful to the Commons, and would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have been ſo, if <hi>Reynards</hi> policy had not been obſerved and put in practice by them. Beſides, <hi>Iſegrim</hi> (for his own part) carried himſelf ſo demurely, and ſpake ſo ſeldom, as even I my ſelf was more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n half perſwaded, he had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his nature, and with his new Gown put on another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, directly contrary to that of his own. But I now clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that a Wolf will be a Wolf, what Coat ſoever he wears. Therefore I am heartily glad his whole Lineage is at this time reduced to their priſtine condition. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that I may not in time to come be upbraided by any <note place="margin">The true Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince.</note> of thoſe ungrateful Beaſts, with the retaining their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I will ſpeedily order the diſtribution of the ſame, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Commons in general, eſpecially, amongſt thoſe who have ſuſtained damage by them.</p>
               <p>The next day the King called all his Lords and Friends to Council, where he declared his intentions of diſtributing
<pb facs="tcp:64820:55"/> the Treaſure of the Wolves among the Commons, and principally among ſuch as had ſuſtained loſs, or injury by them. To this they all aſſented, applauding the Kings No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs. Then the King commanded the Lord <hi>Sly look,</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Firrapel</hi> the Libbard, to order the diſtribution thereof with as much equity as was poſſible.</p>
               <p>Now while this was a doing, the King again called his Lords and Friends about him, and ſaid, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rthy Friends, We unadviſedly and through falſe accuſation condemnediour Chaplain <hi>Bellin,</hi> and his Kindred; therefore, ſince our error is diſcovered, and the Murther for which <hi>Bellin</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is acknowledged by <hi>Reynard,</hi> that falſe Traytor, to be perpetrated by himſelf; it concerns us in ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary manner to recompence the great wrongs that Family hath ſuſtained for ſo long a time, and all that through a miſunderſtanding of ours, and through too great credulity of what we ſaw: for though <hi>Bellin</hi> brought <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yward</hi> the Hare's head to us, yet the Fox <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lew the Hare, and put it in his own Male, and then tyed the Male about <hi>Bellins</hi> Neck; through which notorious crime craftily vailed, by that wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Miſcreant <hi>Reynard,</hi> our judgment was deceived, <hi>Bellin</hi> was put to Death, his Lineage made a prey to the Bear and the Wolf, and we and all our Family brought even to the brink of ruin.</p>
               <p>Theſe words were uttered by the king with ſo great ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, as all his Lords and Friends were very much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected therewith; therefore they ſaid, It is in your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties power to honour and reſpect them, as much as you pleaſe; we all will readily obey in whatſoever your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall command thereabout. The king hearing them thus ſpeak, ſaid, Worthy Friends, ſince you ſo readily have offred to follow our Advice, and obey our Commands, we accept the ſame kindly; and therefore will now offer what we think moſt expedient in this caſe.</p>
               <p>You all know, we by our Proclamation have already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them into our Protection; yet you nor we our ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:64820:56"/> ſuppoſe that a ſufficient recompence; therefore, ſince raiſe the Dead we cannot, to the Living let us ſhew as much kindneſs as ſhall be convenient; for when the Commons perceive that we not only protect, but alſo reſpect <hi>Bellins</hi> Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, they in imitation of us will do the like. And that our reſpect, and the good opinion we have of them, may the more certainly be known to all our Subjects in general, we will give command, that they all behave themſelves lovingly and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iendly towards them; ſo doing undonbtedly, we ſhall unite all our meaner Subjects in love each to other, and we our ſelves be ſo much the more happy.</p>
               <p>This reſolution of the Kings was immediately aſſented to, and put in execution. And from that day forward the Ram's Kindred walked up and down ſafely and found friends and friendly Entertainment in all places whereſoever they came. The King himſelf, and his Nobles obſerving the great Gravity of this Stock by him ſuppoſed to be utterly exſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) made <hi>Bellins</hi> Grandſon his Counſellor; all the other Nobles ſeeing this, entertained one, or more of the Ram's Kindred, to be always reſiding in, or near their own Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. This familiarity with <hi>Bellins</hi> Kindred, wrought an alteration in the King and Lords; for they heretofore were <note place="margin">As evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication corrupts good Manners, ſo on the other hand, good Examples if followed, produce the well-being of Mankind.</note> wont to fare deliciouſly, and to feed on divers ſorts of meats; alſo upon ſlight occaſions to be chalerick and angry; they now ſeeing the great temperance and meekneſs of their new Sociates, began to feed more ſparingly, and not of ſo many ſorts at one time; holding this courſe a while, they found themſelves not ſo prone to choler or anger as before. The King obſerving this change not in himſelf only but in all his Friends and Nobles, was willing to propagate it further; therefore he by publick Proclamation commanded all his Subjects high and low to entertain familiarity with the Ram's Kindred, alſo to take example by them, and follow their Inſtructions in all things tending to ſobriety and love. This Proclamation was exactly obeyed by the Commons in general, who ever after lived in ſuch peace and love, as the
<pb facs="tcp:64820:56"/> like hath ſearcely ever been heard of ſince the beginning of <note place="margin">The height of all Happineſs in this world, conſiſts in the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of King and People.</note> that Kingdom. The King finding this change in all his Subjects univerſally, was highly pleaſed, and rewarded all his Friends nobly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the foregoing Hiſtory, I have not in any wiſe deviated from my firſt intention, which was to frame a Second Part to the delightful <hi>Hiſtory of Reynard the Fox,</hi> which might yield thee both pleaſure and profit. If any one be offended, let his offence be to himſelf; my intent was not to give diſtaſte but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Nor have I in the foregoing Hiſtory let ſlip any Expreſſions tending to the vitiating, or debauching of Youth, but have rather couched my words ſo, as the intelligent may be profited, and the diſingenious not injured. Therefore I deſire this my Labour may be as well taken as meant; If ſo, I ſhall be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to divulge a more ſerious piece, (not or Beaſts, but of Men) ſo ſoon as time and opportunity will permit, Farewell.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:57"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for</hi> Edward Brewſter, <hi>at the Crane in</hi> St. Pauls <hi>Church-yard, ſince the late dreadful fire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or, the Sinner condemned of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; being a Plea for God, againſt all the Uogodly, proving them alone guilty of their own deſtiuction; and that they ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the great Day of Account; not for that they lacked, but only becauſe they neglected the means of their Salvation. And alſo, ſhewing how fallacious and frivolous a Pretence it is in any, to ſay, They would do better if they could; when indeed all men could, and might do better, if they would.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or, Scriptures Self-evidence: To prove its Exiſtence, Authority in it Self, and ſufficiency (in its kind) to aſcertain others, That it is Inſpit'd of God to be the <hi>Only Rule of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed as a Plea for Proteſtants in the Deſence of their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and intended only for the uſe and inſtruction of the Vulgar ſort.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Bible.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of Reynard the Fox.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of Guy Earl of Warwick.</p>
            <p>A uſeful Table of Expences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> revived: a Treatiſe proving, That it is not lawful (and therefore ſinful) for any Man or Woman to eat Blood, viz. the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood of any Creature &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Natural and Artificial Concluſions.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ball's</hi> Catechiſm with the Expoſition.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Roger</hi>'s Righteous Mans Evidence for Heaven 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian advice both to Young and Old, rich and poor, which may ſerve as a Directory at hand, ready to direct all perſons almoſt in every ſtate and condition; under 17 general uſeful heads: By <hi>Tho. Mocket.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſilius Valentinus</hi> laſt Will and Teſtament; which was found hid under a Table of Marble, behind the High Altar in the Cathedral Church of the Imperial City of <hi>Erford,</hi> leaving it there to be found by him whom Gods providence ſhould make worthy.</p>
            <p>There is now in the Preſs two very uſeful Books. The <hi>Apoſtolical Hiſtory,</hi> containing a narration of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> By <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>radock,</hi> B. D. <hi>fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Proſpect of Divine Providence. By <hi>Tho. Crane,</hi> octva.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64820:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
